<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Foure sermons vpon the seuen chiefe vertues or principall effectes of faith and the doctrine of election: wherein euerie man may learne, whother he be Gods childe or no. Preached at Malden in Essex by Master George Gifford, penned from his mouth, and corrected and giuen to the Countesse of Sussex, for a Newyeeres gift.</title>
            <author>Gifford, George, d. 1620.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1582</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 117 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 56 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01724</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11858</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118830</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854037</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854037</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19443</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01724)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19443)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 958:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Foure sermons vpon the seuen chiefe vertues or principall effectes of faith and the doctrine of election: wherein euerie man may learne, whother he be Gods childe or no. Preached at Malden in Essex by Master George Gifford, penned from his mouth, and corrected and giuen to the Countesse of Sussex, for a Newyeeres gift.</title>
                  <author>Gifford, George, d. 1620.</author>
                  <author>Josua, Richard.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[112] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By Thomas Dawson] for Tobie Cooke at the Tigers head in Paules Churchyard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1582.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An edition of: Foure sermons uppon the seven chiefe vertues of faith.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Editor's dedication signed: Richard Iosua Iunior.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [par.]⁴ A-F G⁴.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: colophon lacking.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19443:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19443:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶ Foure Sermons vpon the ſeuen chiefe ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues or principall effectes of <hi>faith, and the doctrine of electi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on:</hi> wherein euerie man may learne, whether he be Gods childe or no.</p>
            <p>Preached at Malden in Eſſex by Maſter <hi>George Gifford,</hi> pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>from his mouth, and cor</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected and giuen to the Counteſſe of <hi>Suſſex,</hi> for a Newyeeres gift.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Iames 2. 18.</bibl>
               <p>Shewe mee thy faith by thy workes.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Jmprinted at Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <hi>don for Tobie Cooke at</hi> the Tigers head in Paules <hi>Churchyard. 1582.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19443:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19443:2"/>
            <head>¶ <hi>To the right honorable</hi> and my very good Lady, the Lady Frauncis, Counteſſe of Suſſex, R. I. her <hi>moſt humble and faithfull ſeruant in</hi> Chriſt, wiſheth all health and godlineſſe, long to continue <hi>with increaſe of vertue and zeale in religion.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue long time wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed (Right Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable) that I might in ſome ſort be able, if not to reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pence which in deed I ſhal neuer, yet at the leaſt to ſhewe ſome token of a grateful minde, for all the ancient kindnes, &amp; louing fauour, which I haue found at your hands: this hath cauſed mee to foreſlip no occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wherby I might haue ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what to preſent you withall, which might tend to your ſoules health: for concerning the thinges which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to the body, as honours, digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb facs="tcp:19443:3"/>
and riches, the high Lorde of Lords hath giuenyou ſo much, that though I woulde neuer ſo faine, yet I cannot benefite you in them: ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing therefore of late a kinſman at home with me, who being, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of a readie hande, hath taken from the mouth of our Preacher, certaine of the Sermons which hee hath preached, whiche beeing againe ouerſeene and corrected, I thought it my dutie, to offer them vnto your honor, as a taſte of thoſe fruites wherewith the Lorde doth feede vs in the Countrie. Beeing a great deale the more bold to doe it, becauſe I know they bee ſuch as ye haue long time ſhewed a loue to taſte of: &amp; I truſt theſe ſhal alſo come vnto you as ripe and timely fruites of pleaſant and delightſome taſte, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they be ſet before you in no golden or ſiluer plate, but as it were
<pb facs="tcp:19443:3"/>
in a woodden platter: for the holie Apoſtle Saint Paule ſaieth, that this treaſure is brought in earthen veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels. I beſeech your honour there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to accept of my poore good will, and to take this my ſmall gifte in good part: which nothing doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of, I pray God to multiplie his bleſſings and gracesvpon you, to his glorie, and your euerlaſting com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your honours in Chriſt,
<hi>Richard Ioſua Senior.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:19443:4"/>
            <head>To the godly Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onſidering that for a Chriſtian, being ſicke in ſoule, and deſiring to bee made ſounde, ſorrowfull in ſpirit, &amp; crauing com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fort, vnquiet in minde, and ſeeking to be at reſt, wounded in conſcience, and woulde bee in ſafetie, tormented in thought, and longeth for releife, hauing offended God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is puniſhed, viſited with affliction, and faine would be deliuered, there is no other ſalue but the worde of God: And knowing alſo, that it is the dutie of euery good chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian in his calling to ſeeke, and thirſt after the aduancement, and increaſe of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſt, &amp; the ouerthrowe &amp; vtter confuſion of blindneſſe, errour, popery, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, and to bee ſhort, of all the power of Antichriſt: I haue thought it my dutie the rather (Gentle Reader) to requeſt here vnto, by ſundrie godly men my friends, the Preacher hereof to publiſh this booke con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining ſundrie points of doctrine tending to the comfort of the godly, &amp; the aſſurance
<pb facs="tcp:19443:4"/>
of their ſaluation: as alſo diuers confutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ſects and hereſies, which to him that readeth it with a well diſpoſed minde, ſhall be no leſſe profitable, then it is briefe. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel not at the ſhortneſſe of it: the cauſe thereof is this, that the repetition in the beginning of euery ſermon, to auoid tediouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, is omitted. Looke not for (I pray thee) fineſſe of ſpeeche, or eloquence in the reading hereof: but way the matter deepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and applie it to thy ſelfe effectually, that thou mayeſt reape profite hereout, to thy ſoules health, and comfort, the which God graunt thee, for his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt his ſake.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in Chriſt,
Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Ioſua Iunior.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:19443:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19443:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The firſt Sermon vpon the</hi> firſt Chapter of the ſecond Epiſtle of Saint Peter.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> Simon Peter a ſeruant and an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of Ieſus Chriſte, to you which haue obtained like precious faith with vs by the righteouſnes of our God and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Grace &amp; peace be multiplied to you, through the acknowledging of god and of our Lord Ieſus.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 According as his diuine power hath giuen vnto vs all things that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine vnto life and Godlineſſe, through the acknowledging of him, that hath called vs vnto glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and vertue.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 Whereby moſt great and precious promiſes are giuen vnto vs, that by them yee ſhould bee partakers of the diuine nature, in that yee flee the corruption which is in the world through luſt.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19443:6"/>
BEfore we begin to handle or intreate of the wordes of this text, it ſhall not be amiſſe to note to whom &amp; when this Epiſtle was written. Concerning the firſt of theſe, it appeareth by the third chap. and 1. ver. that it was written vnto the ſame that the former Epiſtle was. For thus he ſpeaketh. This ſecond Epiſtle I write vnto you, beloued, in which I ſtirre vp your ſincere minde, by putting you in remembrance: now theſe were the Iewes which were ſcattered abroade in the diſperſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> through diuers countries, as it is expreſſed in the firſt chap. of the former Epiſtle: for the Iewes were ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially his charge, as the care of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles was committed vnto Paul. Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians the 2. chapter, 7. and 8. verſes. The wordes are theſe: when they ſawe that the Goſpell of the vncircumciſion was committed to mee, as the Goſpell ouer the circumciſion was vnto Peter: for he was mightie by Peter in the Apoſtlſhip, ouer the circumciſion, was alſo mightie by me towards the Gentiles. For the 2. this Epiſtle was written by Peter in his extreme age, when he had euen finiſhed
<pb facs="tcp:19443:6"/>
his courſe, and was readie to lay downe his tabernacle, as he ſpeaketh here in the 14. verſ. As for the occaſions which mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued him to write, they ſhall appeare in the particular handling of the matters.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Now let vs come to the wordes of the text, the 1. verſe hath two members: In the former he ſetteth foorth his own dignitie, that he is not only a ſeruant of God, but a principall ſeruant, and one which commeth vnto them as the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour of god, to the end they might knowe that they had to doe with God, and not with men, and ſo ſubmit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to the doctrine &amp; meſſage which he brought: for whatſoeuer God ſpake by the Apoſtles, he ſo guided their tong &amp; pen by his ſpirite, that nothing which they ſpake or wrote, was their own, but altogether his. In the ſecond member, he ſetteth forth the dignity which thoſe to whom he writ had with himſelfe: in theſe wordes, <hi>To thoſe which haue obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the like precious faith with vs:</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, although I be aboue you in the Apoſtolik dignitie and function, yet you are equal with me &amp; with the reſt of
<pb facs="tcp:19443:7"/>
the Apoſtles in the chiefe and principall dignitie, &amp; in that wherein all happines doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſt, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our precious faith. Here it may bee demaunded, howe Saint Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter can aſcribe vnto them a faith equall or like precious with his owne, ſeeing he did ſo farre excell them in giftes and graces, as in knowledge, &amp; ſtrength of faith. The anſwer is eaſie inough, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that this compariſon is not made in the meaſure &amp; qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tity of faith, for ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſome haue excelled others farre, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God doth not giue his gifts to all alike: but in the effect, which is the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending of Chriſt with al his merits, which the weak faith doth as wel as the ſtrong, and therefore in this reſpect is equally precious. This I ſpeake, not to make any ſlouthfull, when as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures do pricke vs forwarde ſo much to ſeeke increaſe of faith, but for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and hartening of the weake, which feeling their infirmitie and weaknes of faith, if it were not for this which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpeaketh, might doubt whether they were partakers of the ſame happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with them; now hearing this, they
<pb facs="tcp:19443:7"/>
may be wel aſſured, al though their faith ſhould be but as a grain of muſtard ſeed, yet if it bee true faith, it coupleth them to Chriſte, and maketh them partakers of redemption, to haue their ſinnes wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed away in his blood of righteouſnes, to be couered with his obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of life, to be heires of the kingdome of glorie, as wel as the faith of Peter, or any other. Vnto this is alſo ioyned that wherin the ſtablenes of this their faith doth ſtande, as vpon a ſure foundation, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of God and of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſte. And indeede the building of faith is ſo waightie, and the frame ſo heauie, that it can ſtande vpon no other foundation but this, that is to ſay, the righteouſneſſe, faithfulneſſe, or truth of God which cannot lie. For if we would perſwade a man to beleeue by this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that the thing which wee ſpeake, is that which hath been taught by diuers men of great learning &amp; ſingular god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines: yet becauſe we know that al men are lyers, except wee bee ſure that the things which they ſpeak, be thoſe which God hath ſpoken, wee ſhall ſtill wauer,
<pb facs="tcp:19443:8"/>
and our faith ſhalbe no faith, which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone can reſt in the authoritie of God, and not of men.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The ſeconde verſe conteineth his ſalutation, euen that which is common to him with Paul &amp; the other Apoſtles: wiſhing grace and peace, to thoſe vnto whom they write. And this they do, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is the chiefe ſcope and principal ende of their miniſterie, to bring men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine into Gods fauour, &amp; to be recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled vnto him. Of this thing ſpeaketh S. Paul, 2. Cor. 5. chap. ver. 18. ſaying. All things are of God which hath reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciled vs to himſelf by Ieſus Chriſt. And hath giuen vnto vs the miniſterie of reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation, for God was in Chriſte and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled the worlde to himſelfe, not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting their ſinnes vnto them: and hath committed to vs the word of reconcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation. Now thé are we Ambaſſadors for Chriſt, as though God did beſeeche you through vs, wee pray you in Chriſte his ſteede, that you bee reconciled to God. This beeing the chiefe end of their tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, cauſeth them ſo earneſtly to wiſh it for the people: and to bee ſo ſerious,
<pb facs="tcp:19443:8"/>
not only in teaching them this general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but alſo pointing out as it were with the finger, the way to the ſame: and that not onelie in their doctrine, but alſo in their liues. Whoſoeuer digreſſeth or caſteth his eyes aſide from this marke &amp; ende of his miniſterie, ceaſeth to bee the Miniſter of Chriſte. As for example, If hee preach the Goſpell to purchaſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowme, eſtimation, wealth of caſe, to himſelfe, and not to ſeeke this reconcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation betweene God and men, and to haue grace and peace multiplied vppon them, he may wel ſometimes preach the truth, but not truly.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe, thoſe parentes whiche ſet foorth their children to learning, with this minde: My ſonne ſhall liue an eaſie and merie life, hee ſhal get ſome liuings, promotions, &amp; dignities in the Church: do lay a corrupt and rotten foundation, &amp; haue not learned this doctrine of the Apoſtle, and therefore the building fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes agreeably for the moſt, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they come to haue learning, not forgetting this leſſon which they learned of their fathers, doe become greedie cathers of
<pb facs="tcp:19443:9"/>
benefices and promotions, rather then carefull feeders of the flocke of Chriſt. But here it may be obiected, how the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle can wiſh that grace which is the free fauour of God, ſhould be multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vpon them, ſeeing that Gods loue &amp; fauor doth not increaſe nor diminiſhe, but hee loueth and fauoureth alwayes alike, being ſubiect to no alteration or change. This may wel be anſwered, that Sainte Peter doeth not ſpeake heere of grace, as it is in it ſelfe in God towardes me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but of their feeling the ſame, which groweth by degrees from leſſe to grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and becauſe it is a thing ſo precious, the Apoſtle wiſheth that it may be mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied vpon them. Hee expreſſeth the meane to be the knowledge &amp; acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging of God, and of Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3</hi> According as his diuine power hath giuen vnto vs al things that perteine vnto life &amp; godlines, through the acknowledging of him that hath called vs vnto glory and vertue.</p>
            <p>This is fitly ioyned to the former
<pb facs="tcp:19443:9"/>
verſe, to ſhewe that the aboundance of grace and peace is not without cauſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired at our handes, as if the Apoſtle ſhoulde ſay, You are not to content nor to ſatisfie your ſelues with a ſcant mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Gods giftes and graces, ſeeing that there is offred vnto you, &amp; ſet forth in Chriſt, vnto whom you may reſort as to a ſtorehouſe fully furniſhed with all treaſures, all things which partain to life and godlineſſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, we haue to obſerue in this verſe, when hee ſaith that all thinges are giuen vnto vs by his diuine power, that here is nothing left in the worke of our ſaluation vnto our ſelues: ſo that it muſt needes follow, that theſe which defend free will, doe not ſpeake with the ſame ſpirite which the Apoſtle doth here. For ſetting forth a contrary doctrine to this it muſt needes proceed from a contrary ſpirite. The Apoſtle doth not ſay heere, that all thoſe thinges which wee want, through the weakeneſſe of our nature, ſhalbe ſupplied, but to ſhewe that there is nothing in vs at all, but that wee are quite ſtript of all things which pertaine
<pb facs="tcp:19443:10"/>
to life and godlineſſe, Hee ſpeaketh not of repairing or helping in ſome parte, but of a whole and free gifte in euerie part: when he ſaith whithout exception that all thinges are giuen vnto vs by the diuine power, which pertaine vnto life, and godlines: and ſo this doctrine doth chalenge all the praiſe and glory of our ſaluation to God alone.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, it may be demanded why the Apoſtle ſhoulde ſay that all thinges are giuen vnto vs by the diuine power or Godhead of our Sauiour Chriſte, when it is manifeſt that wee ferche all thinges from his manhood: and therefore hee ſaith in the 6. chap. of S. Iohn, verſe 46. I am the bread of life: and againe in the 54. verſe of that ſame chapter, Hee that eateth my fleſh, and drinketh my blood I will raiſe him vp in the laſt day: For my fleſhe is meate indeede, and my blood is drink indeed: by this it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, that life is giuen vnto the worlde, by the manhood of Chriſte. The an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere is eaſie, that Chriſte in his man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoode is a creature, and therefore hath nothing of his owne, but whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="tcp:19443:10"/>
is in him, as to bee the life of the worlde, and the light of men, and to haue in him al the treaſures of wiſdom: This commeth from the diuine nature, which dwelleth in him bodily, as Saint Paule ſpeaketh. Nowe the cauſe why all theſe are put into the manhoode of Chriſte, is that from thence wee maye bee partakers of them: for ſolong as they haue reſidence onely in God, wee are ſo farre remoued from him that by no meanes wee can approche or come neere vnto him to drawe out of him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny drop of the ſame. Therefore though all things bee giuen vs by this meanes, that GOD hath put them into the fleſhe of Chriſt, and ſo is come downe neere vnto vs, that wee may lay faſt hold of him: yet neuertheleſſe becauſe the proprietie of them remaineth ſtill in the diuine nature, the gifte of them is heere aſcribed vnto the power there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, we are to note in this verſe, that the Apoſtle doeth briefly ſet downe the ende and ſumme of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and of all theſe giftes, when he
<pb facs="tcp:19443:11"/>
ſaith, which pertaine to life and godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: for in theſe two wordes, vnto which the other two do anſwere, which are ſet downe in the latter ende of the verſe, glorie and vertue, all thoſe giftes are contained. For that which hee expreſſed firſt by life, heere by glorie, that which before he called godlineſſe, here he calleth vertue: they are as much as to ſay, eternall felicitie, and life with glorie, and the way which we muſt paſſe through to the ſame, which is godlines and vertue. Here we are to take great heede, that wee doe not ſeuer or ſunder thoſe thinges which the Lorde himſelfe hath ſo neerely coupled and linked to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. And this admonition is ſo much the more neceſſarie, becauſe there are very many carnall profeſſors and beaſtly abuſers of chriſtianity, which doe ſeeme very willingly and gladly to imbrace the promiſes of the Goſpell, concerning redemption and eternall life purchaſed in Chriſte Ieſus: and they make great boaſt that they looke for their parte in the ſame as well as any other, &amp; yet they looke nothing at al to this godlines and
<pb facs="tcp:19443:11"/>
vertue, through which we muſt paſſe vn to it, for God hath not called vs, but as hee ſaith heere, to glorie and vertue, ſo that whom ſoeuer the Lorde hath called to know him aright, and ſo to be made heires of eternall glorie, he hath alſo gar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſhed them with vertues and graces of the ſpirite of ſanctification. Vntill ſuch time therefore, as there ſhall riſe vp a new Peter, which with contrary pen ſhal write a newe and contrary goſpell, theſe men ſhall neuer aſſure them ſelues, nor yet perſwade others that they ſhall euer come to the kingdome of God, ſeeing they goe a quite contrarie way.</p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>Whereby moſt great and precious promiſes are giuen vnto vs,</hi> &amp;c. Now hee ſheweth by what meanes or by what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments the diuine power doeth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow thoſe giftes vpon vs, and the ſame are as hee calleth them, moſt great and precious promiſes which are giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto vs, whereby we are called to glorie and vertue, as hee ſpeaketh in the former verſe: theſe are called moſt great &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, becauſe the things which are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered vnto vs in the goſpel of Chriſt, for
<pb facs="tcp:19443:12"/>
greatnes &amp; dignity are inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>parable. For what ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſeeke out to match with this that here is offered vnto vs: namely the remiſſion of our ſins in the blood of his ſonne, deliuerance &amp; freedom from the thraldom of Satan &amp; power of darknes, that of damned creatutes &amp; children of his wrath, he hath giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs this high dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to be his ſonnes &amp; daughters: &amp; as S. Iohn ſaith, Reue. I. Chriſt hath waſhed vs in his blood, and made vs kinges and prieſts to god his father: what a change is this, from the loweſt miſery, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the gulf of hel, to be lifted vp, to the higheſt dignitie, to be glorified with God in the kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of heuen? Becauſe therfore theſe things are the greateſt &amp; moſt honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, S. Peter calleth the promiſes of the goſpel, moſt great &amp; precious. But wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doeth the apoſtle aſcribe all to the doctrine of the goſpel? for whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaith, that by theſe we are made partakers of the diuine nature, hee includeth all, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is by the goſpel that we are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led home to the Lord: for although hee vtter his will vnto vs in his law, yet ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in hee ſheweth himſelfe none otherwiſe
<pb facs="tcp:19443:12"/>
vnto vs, but as a ſeuere iudge, we can ſee nothing there, but the dreadful curſe, &amp; vengeance of eternall fire: his brightnes appeareth therein, but we be not able to beholde the ſame, but are daſeled with the ſight therof, amazed &amp; confounded ſo that we cannot but runne from him, bicauſe there is nothing but that which is terrible. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trariwiſe, in the Goſpel, he hath reuealed himſelfe in the face of his ſonne, where hee ſheweth an exceeding glory, but with ſuch fatherly loue, &amp; pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, ſuch abu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dance of mercie, and ſweete allurements, by which he calleth vs and draweth vs to himſelf: that here wee are able to looke vpon him with open face, and heere his countenance is ſo cheere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, that the ſoule which hath once, with the eye of faith ſeene but a glimſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, is ſo inflamed and rauiſhed with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of a neerer and fuller ſight<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that it can neuer bee ſatisfied. For this cauſe Saint Paule making compariſon betweene the miniſterie of the Lawe and the miniſterie of the Goſpell. 2. Corinthians, 3. Termeth that the miniſtration of death, and the letter
<pb facs="tcp:19443:13"/>
which killeth: and this the miniſtration of the ſpirit which giueth life. Which by the way alſo is to bee obſerued, becauſe there be among vs at this day many fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike braines: namely thoſe of the Family of loue, which call the true &amp; ſound in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreting of the word, the literal ſenſe, or the letter which killeth, &amp; their owne groſſe and fooliſh allegories the ſpirite: not knowing that S. Peter ſpeaketh of the difference betweene the Lawe, and the Goſpel. Here alſo appeareth of what price and dignitie the goſpel is: for who can ſet foorth the worthineſſe of this, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaith, that by theſe promiſes we are made partakers of the diuine nature we were indeed at the firſt created after the Image of God, and ſo partakers of his nature: but we loſt all this with our firſt parents, &amp; in ſteede thereof we were made partakers of the diueliſh nature, bearing his Image and fulfilling: his luſtes. Nowe by faith in the Goſpel, this image is reſtored and built vp in vs againe, whileſt we receiue the ſpirite of ſanctification ioyned with the ſame. If men did know this firſt, that all happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb facs="tcp:19443:13"/>
in men is to be made partakers of the nature of God, &amp; to communicate with him: and then that this is wrought only by the Goſpel: men woulde not ſo lothſomely deſpiſe it, and preferre euery light commoditie, and trifling pleaſure before it: men woulde not ſeeke to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace &amp; ſlander it: men would not be ſo ſoone wearie in hearing of it, nor thinke euery houre ten while they bee at it. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally men, vnleſſe they were mad men, would not as they do now almoſt euery where, thinke them ſelues beſt at eaſe when it is furtheſt from them: for who would willingly throwe himſelfe head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to deſtruction; who would ſo play the mad beaſtes, as to thruſt God from them, &amp; refuſe to bee made partakers of his heauenly nature? which al they doe, that haue as yet felt no ſweetneſſe in the Goſpell, or at leaſt haue ſo little taſted it that it can ſcarſe obtaine colde lone at their hands. But there needeth ſomwhat to be ſaid vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the phraſe of ſpech which S. Peter vſeth, for it is ſomewhat hard to ſome, &amp; as it was in old time fouly abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by heretikes, ſo is it wickedly at this
<pb facs="tcp:19443:14"/>
day peruerted by the louely Familie, which holding this doctrine that men are deified, and God is hominified, as their language is, meaning that the very eſſence and ſubſtance of God, is tranſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed into men, and his ſubſtance &amp; theirs mingled together, take great holde of this, that the Apoſtle ſaith, wee are made partakers of the diuine nature. But you ſhal ſee that euery ſimple man may eaſily confute the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: if we aſke what the nature of an horſe is, wil a man anſwere that he is made of the earth: then a horſe and a man are both of one nature, for man is alſo made of the earth: it is manifeſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that none is ſo fooliſh but hee will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that when we ſpeake of the nature of any thing, we meane not the ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, but the qualities &amp; properties: euen ſo in this place we muſt needs graunt, that by the diuine nature in this place is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing els ment, but that there ſhould be ſuch a nature and ſuch qualities in men, as may carrye a reſemblance of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine nature: as for example, god is holy, wee muſt bee holy, he is pure, good, iuſt, gracious, bountiful, louing, &amp; merciful,
<pb facs="tcp:19443:14"/>
all theſe and ſuch like muſt be alſo in vs: we ſhal alſo come to be partakers of life, of glory, of ioye, of happineſſe, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternitie, and ſo in a neerer ſorte to bee partakers of the diuine nature. What are all thoſe now the better, which haue ſo receiued the precious promiſes, that their qualities are euen as agreeable to the nature of GOD, as light is with darkeneſſe, or Heauen with Hell, or Chriſte with Beliall: Sith ſo manie ſhamefull and beaſtly ſinnes, flowe and raigne in them, which are ſo many partakinges of the Diueliſhe nature, let them for ſhame denye that they haue ought wherein they communicate with GOD, in anye thing ſauing a bare profeſſion. Then what is it which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a good man; The promiſes of the Goſpell. What is it which bringeth life and ſaluation? The Goſpel. Who are they which haue imbraced the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, &amp; haue the true and liuely faith: The holy. Who are they whom God hath called to life eternall, to bee thoſe whome hee loueth as children, bearing his Image; The pure and vndefiled.
<pb facs="tcp:19443:15"/>
in the laſt clauſe of this verſe he ſheweth his meaning very plainly, In that, ſaieth hee yee flie the corruptions which are in the world through luſt, this is the way to bee made partakers of the diuine na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, for as corruptions and filthie defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linges the more they cleaue vnto vs, the more they ſeparate vs from the Lord, ſo contrariwiſe the more a man doeth flie and eſchewe them, ſo much the neerer hee doeth approch vnto God, who is the fountaine of all puritie. We are here to note that S. Peter maketh al corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and naughtineſſe in the worlde to ſpring out of concupiſcence, or as it is vſually tranſlated, luſt: where wee muſt learne firſt, what this concupiſcence or luſt is, which is heere ſaide to bee as it were the ſeate of ſinne, and indeede it is the roote and fountaine, out of which groweth &amp; floweth al euill that is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in the world, either in thought, worde, or deede: to be ſhort, this is that which is forbidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the tenth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaith, Thou ſhalt not couer: at leaſt ſo much of it is forbidden there, as pertaineth to the ſecond table, that is
<pb facs="tcp:19443:15"/>
the roote &amp; fountaine of all euil againſt men, for there is nothing recited in the ſame laſt commandement, but towarde men: &amp; when our Sauiour Chriſt ſetteth foorth the ſumme of the firſt table, hee ſaith it is to loue the Lorde with all the heart, with al the ſoule, &amp;c. Now where the whole hart is required, there concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence muſt needs be forbidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but ye wil ſay, what is it; wherin doth it conſiſt? It is not in deeds, words, nor thoughts, but a more cloſe &amp; inward ſicknes, bred as they ſay, in the bones, the natural blot &amp; ſpot of originall ſinne, which we haue by inheritance, from our firſt parents, &amp; bring with vs out of our mothers wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>b, out of which al euil thoughts &amp; deſires do ariſe in vs. S. Iames in the firſt chap. of his Epiſtle maketh it the wombe &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which conceiueth &amp; bringeth forth ſinne: Let no man (ſaith hee) when he is tempted, ſay, I am tempted of God, for God cannot be tempted with euill, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pteth he any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but euery one is tempted when he is drawne away by his own concupiſcence, &amp; is entiſed: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> luſt when it hath conceiued, bringeth forth
<pb facs="tcp:19443:16"/>
ſinne, &amp; ſinne whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is finiſhed bringeth forth death. The firſt thing we haue here to note in this doctrine is this: that all corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is of our ſelues, not comming from any outward cauſe: it is true that Satan is an inſtrument, &amp; as it were the bellowes to ſtirre and kindle in vs the luſtes of ſinne, and beareth a very great ſtroke in the matter: but if it were not for this concupiſcence that is in vs, hee coulde not bring his matters to paſſe, the prouocations and alurementes of wicked men, are ſo many meanes to driue vs and draw vs into ſinne, but yet the cauſe is in our ſelues. A chiefe point to bee obſerued that wee may learne to condemne our ſelues when wee haue done amiſſe, and not after the maner of men, which looke when they haue faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted howe they may disburthen them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and be diſcharged of the blame, and therefore they will either crie out of the Diuell, as though hee, as they ſay, ought them a ſhame, or els they will ſay, woe worth ſuch or ſuche that euer I knew them, if it had not been for them, I ſhould not haue done thus. The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete
<pb facs="tcp:19443:16"/>
Dauid when hee had committed murther and adultery, being reprooued by Nathan, although hee knewe right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel that the Diuel was a great furtherer in the matter: likewiſe hee might haue thought vpon the fonde dealing of the woman, which ſo indiſcretly waſhed her ſelfe in ſuch a place as others might ſee her: yet hee letteth theſe goe, and to the ende hee may wholy and fully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne himſelf, he looketh home to the welſpring of all this foule and beaſtly ſinne, and ſaith, Beholde I was borne in wickedneſſe, and in ſinne hath my mother conceiued mee: as if he ſhoulde ſay, O Lorde, I cannot ſeeke any way to be excuſed, for all this rebellion againſt thee, is conceiued and bred in mine owne corrupt breſt, I brought the roote of it from my mothers wombe. This is a good leſſion for vs to learne: for ſo long as wee doe not knowe it, but like partial and corrupt Iudges go about to excuſe our ſelues, &amp; to rid our hands of that we haue committed, we ſhal neuer come to any ſincere repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Further, weare here to obſerue in this place that al corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:19443:17"/>
comming from this luſt, if wee will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent indeede, wee muſt begin heere. For if they bee changed onely in their out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde deedes and wordes, and this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſicknes not healed, they haue gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned nothing, no more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a man which would deſtroy a tree, and doth no more then loppe &amp; ſhred of certaine boughes and twigges, leauing the ſtumpe and roote behynde: for ſo long as this doth liue in them, they may well ſeeme in the eyes of men, to bee very great conuerts, if they bee ignorant idiots, are become ſuche as haue gotten ſome ſkill and knowledge: from drunkardes, ruffians, adulterers, and ſuche like, they become ſober and modeſt, and of good behaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our: as this may bee done before men, and yet the hart nothing altered before God: for there bee many cauſes which may mooue men to ſeeme outwardlye to bee godly, when the hearte within is fraught with loathſome luſtes, and full of rotten corruptions, whiche make men ſtill altogether abhominable be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God. To bee ſhort therefore a man ſhall neuet rightly iudge of him ſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:19443:17"/>
whether hee haue repented, vnleſſe hee looke to the bottome of this ſore, that it may be healed. The greateſt multitude of men, being as blind as beetles in this point, imagine that repentance, is a very light &amp; eaſie thing, which they can haue when they liſt: when a man of wiſdome ſaith this, that here lieth ſo deep a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that heere be rootes which are hard to be pulled vp, hee is moued to bee the more carefull, leaſt he deceiue himſelfe. Looke therefore euery man to his thoughts, for by them is the trial made: if the thoughts be cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged, &amp; the inward deſires altered, ſo that of prophane and worldly, they are become holy and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly: then hee may boldly ſay, I haue a newe hearte, and there is a right ſpirite renued in mee, I haue repented, I haue not plaide the hypocrite, I feele an vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right heart toward God, I feele the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt fountaine ſtopped, ſo that the filthy matter, and ſtinking mudde doeth not boyle foorth as it did. It may alſo bee demaunded heere, whether this iuſte bee not a ſinne or a corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:19443:18"/>
of it ſelfe, becauſe S. Peter ſaith, that corruption reſteth in it. The place which I alleadged out of the 51. Pſalme, doeth prooue it to bee a ſinne: alſo it may bee proued out of the fifth to the Romans, Where Saint Paule proueth that infants haue ſinne, becauſe they are ſubiect to death, which is the reward of ſinne, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though as hee ſaith, they ſinne not after the ſimilitude of the tranſgreſſion of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam. Therefore if wee had none other but this, it were enough to condemne vs, and vtterly to caſt vs away. Let vs neuer ceaſe therefore, vntill wee feele a change in our ſelues, euen in this ſecrete infection, for otherwiſe wee ſhall neuer bee able to flie the corruptions whiche are in the world, or as Saint Iames ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in the firſt Chapter of his Epiſtle, to keepe our ſelues vnſpotted of the worlde, ſo long as wee carie the corrupt world in our own breſt: neither ſhal our religion be pure, for thus it is ſaide, if any man among you ſeemeth religious and refraineth not his tongue, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth his owne hearte, this mans re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is vaine. Pure religion and vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed
<pb facs="tcp:19443:18"/>
before God, euen the father is this, to viſite the fatherleſſe and widowes in their diſtreſſe, and to keepe himſelfe vnſpotted of the worlde.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:19443:19"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The ſeconde Sermon vpon</hi> the 5. 6. and 7. verſes.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p n="5">5 Therfore giue euen al diligence ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, ioyne moreouer vertue with your faith: &amp; with vertue know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge:</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> And with knowledge, temperaunce: and with temperaunce, patience: and with patience, godlines:</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7</hi> And with godlines, brotherly kinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: and with brotherly kindnes, loue.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>ANd hereunto giue al diligence, &amp;c. He hath declared in the former ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, among other chief matters: this one eſpeciallv, to howe great holineſſe and pureneſſe through ſanctification, we be called: which was chiefly expreſſed in theſe wordes, that by them yee may bee made partakers of the diuine nature, in that yee flie the corruption which is in the worlde through luſt: vnto this now he ioyneth an exhortation, requiring at their handes not only to put to their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, but alſo, as hee ſaith, euen all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence,
<pb facs="tcp:19443:19"/>
For as it is the greateſt and chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt thing which we are to looke after, ſo there is required at our handes, to giue our principal care and ſtudie thereunto: this equitie muſt eaſily be graunted, that if we cannot obteine or get the thinges of this life, which are ſmall in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, vnleſſe wee put to our diligence, for God will haue it to bee ſo, that then of good right<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> looke howe much heauenly things exceede in dignitie, the earthly, ſo much muſt the care and diligence beſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed vpon them exceed. How far almoſt are all men from this doctrine both in practiſe and iudgement: firſt, when we ſee the exceeding trauel &amp; paines which they ſticke not willingly to beſtowe, in getting the beggerly traſh of this world, either riches or honours: they wil ryde and run, early and late by night and by day, by ſea and by land, winter and ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, wearing out their bodies, almoſt pine and ſterue themſelues with hunger and bearing their braines with as great diligence as can be poſſible: but when it commeth to theſe things which S. Peter ſpeaketh, as things of no price, they paſſ
<pb facs="tcp:19443:20"/>
by them, in ſuch wiſe, that they are here euen as ſlouthfull and careleſſe, as they are diligent in the other. For iudgement in this behalfe, if a man talke with theſe worldly men, they wil ſhew their minde and opinion, aske them why they bee ſo careful for theſe worldly things, their an ſwere is readie, wee ſhal otherwiſe come ſhort of them, and go without them: &amp; why do ye not ſeeke as faſt for heauenly thinges, they be the greateſt: they be in deede the greateſt, but we commit that to God, wee wil not meddle with that. Thus they ſhift off the care of godlines, as though god did not require it at their hands: neuer hearing of this which S. Peter requireth: wee muſt take heede of this, giuing eare to god, who teacheth vs this leſſon by the holy Apoſtle: for if we let this paſſe, we are moſt miſerable: here alſo when wee are warned to giue al di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, appeareth plainely howe harde a thing it is to flie from corrupt luſtes: for if it were an eaſie thing to be done leſſe diligence might ſerue: but ſinne cleaueth neere and ſticketh faſt in vs, &amp; is not eaſily ſhaken of: it is deepely roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb facs="tcp:19443:20"/>
ſo that vnleſſe we digge very deepe, wee are ſure to leaue the rootes ſtil be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde, which wil growe &amp; ſpring againe as faſt as before, yea oftentimes ſeeming to bee dead, they ſodeinly reuiue: ſo that wee are ſet a worke while we liue heere without any intermiſſion, to be ſtill toy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to pul vp theſe weedes, the ground is ſo ranke, that in a very ſhort time it will bee wholy ouergrowne. Therefore ſuch as deſpiſe the meanes which God hath appointed, or vſe them ouer negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently, muſt needes haue their heart o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer growne with theſe ſtinking weeds of luſt and concupiſcence: and ſo if euer there be any good ſeed in them, as good motions or inclinations to feare God, they are by and by choked, ſo that they can bring foorth no fruite, or at leaſt no ripe and timely fruite.</p>
            <p>But heere may be obiected, that this agreeth not with the former ſaying, that the diuine power hath giuen vs al thinges which pertaine to life and godlineſſe, there hee aſcribeth all to God, and taketh all from vs, heere he ſeemeth to giue ſomewhat vnto our
<pb facs="tcp:19443:21"/>
diligence, and ſo to eſtabliſhe freewill in vs. We muſt anſwere here that God wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth al in al, &amp; alone ſtriketh the ſtroke, yet he doeth not worke in vs, as the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penter or Maſon worketh vpon the log and the ſtone, which haue no feeling of that which is done vpon them, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore nothing of them is required: but we haue a wil in vs &amp; reaſon, which of them ſelues beeing corrupt, doe nothing but hinder this worke, vntill ſuche time as god hath faſhioned them anew; we haue appetites &amp; affections in vs, but of them ſelues meere rebels: theſe he <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>eth and ſubdueth. So that this worke of God in vs, is not without a feeling of it, for hee moueth vs to wil, to deſire, to ſorow, to reioyce, &amp; ſuch like, ſo that our diligence is required, becauſe he worketh in none but he doth make them diligent; heere is ſtil then that which God doth beſtow vpon vs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and not that which we haue of ourſelues. By this place al thoſe are an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, which cloke and defende them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in then naughtineſſe and ſlouth in the ſeruice of God, after this manner: we haue that which God hath giuen vs,
<pb facs="tcp:19443:21"/>
all men are not alike godlye, euerie man cannot doe as you doe: when their own heart and conſcience doeth tell euery of them the contrary, ſaying, thou art care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, and negligent, thou haſt as much as thou deſireſt: for God doth increaſe all gifts and graces in thoſe which vſe al di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence in ſeeking after him. Let vs learne therefore, brethren, to put in practiſe al thoſe thinges which are heere taught, to giue greater diligence, and ſo beate our braine more earneſtly about heauenly thinges, then about theſe earthly, to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour &amp; trauell more for godlines, then for treaſures and riches. Which if we do, we ſhall feele increaſe of ſtrength to caſt out corrupt luſts, although not ſo much as faine we would, yet God being true wee ſhall haue ſo much that wee cannot faile nor miſſe of our deſire. It foloweth, ioyne moreouer vertue with your faith, &amp;c. Saint Peter knoweth what babes we be, how vnable to guide our ſteppes in the pathes of godlines, and that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth him not onlie to mooue and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade to godlines, but euen as it were taking vs by the hande, and teaching vs
<pb facs="tcp:19443:22"/>
howe to treade euery ſteppe, hee rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth particulerlye the thinges wherein wee are to trauell, when he ſaith, Ioyne moreouer with your faith, vertue, with vertue knowledge, with knowledge, te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peraunce, with temperaunce, patience, with patience, godlines, and with god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, brotherly kindeneſſe, and with brotherly kindneſſe loue.</p>
            <p>Faith heere is ſet in the firſt place, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which all the other muſt beeioyned, becauſe without it wee cannot by any meanes pleaſe God, it doth iuſtifie vs be fore god alone, but yet it doth not go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, neither is it dead and fruitleſſe, for theſe things do accompany the ſame. In the next place therefore, he coupleth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this, vertue, which is generally put for all the fruites of faith, and all the duties of a godly life. Theſe cannot bee wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, but by and by it muſt needs folow, that the faith is a dead faith, not able to iuſtifie vs before God, nor to giue life: it cannot indeede bee rightly termed any other then a ſhadowe or dumbe picture of faith, whiche may carie ſome ſhewe
<pb facs="tcp:19443:22"/>
and colour of that which it reſembleth. Euen as wee ſee ſome painter ſo skilful, that he can caſt ſuch colours in painting fire, that at the firſt bluſh it might make a man iudge it to be fire in deede: but if a man holde his hand to it, to feele for ſome heate, and to make triall by the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectes, a childe will be able to iudge eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that it is but a dead image, becauſe the effectes are wanting. Euen ſo there be very many men, as cunning as any painter, to make a ſhew of faith, through great bragges and vaunts, that God is their God, &amp; that they al put their whole truſt in him, that they looke to be ſaued as well as the beſt, yea though but a few, yet they hope to bee of the number of thoſe. Let vs looke therefore that we be not deceiued here, let not the outwarde appearaunce beguile vs, but let vs come to the true triall, if there be as much ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue in their life, as there was heate in the foreſaide fire, then knowe that it is euen as good a faith, as that is a fire. For yee maye as well ſeparate fire from the heate thereof, as faith from good and
<pb facs="tcp:19443:23"/>
godly vertues, which are the fruits ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of-What ſhal then bee ſaide of all thoſe from whom do flow ſo many filthie ſins, that ſcarce at any time doeth appeare in them, ſo much as a ſhadowe of vertue? they cannot deceiue any wiſe man, much leſſe ſhall they bee able to deceiue God, Let euery one therefore take heede that hee deceiue not himſelfe, to thinke that he is richly indued with faith, when hee is ſo poore in vertue, for if the latter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound, wee are ſure the former doth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo abounde. For wee muſt trie our faith by our vertues. Next he willeth to ioyne knowledge vnto vertue. Theſe three are general, faith, vertue, &amp; knowledge, and are ſo lincked together, that they cannot be ſundered. For faith is not a blind fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſie whiche man doeth imagine of his owne braine, but it is begun in the right knowledge of Gods will, and increaſeth and groweth by the ſame: it is alſo the rule and ſquare to meaſure and guide al vertue by: for we muſt not thinke, that that is good which ſeemeth ſo vnto our reaſon, but that which God in his reuea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led will hath called good: vnleſſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:19443:23"/>
vertue did growe in vs, wee cannot haue it, before wee become ſkilfull, and haue learned it out of the woorde of God. For this cauſe the Apoſtle mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing theſe excellent men to increaſe in godlineſſe, ſheweth them the way, when hee willeth them to increaſe in knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
            <p>Nowe if wee marke well, what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of men they were to whome hee wrote, namelye, no babes nor younge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linges in the Goſpel, for hee ſaide they had obteined like precious faith with him, and after warde in this Chapter hee ſaieth, they did knowe and were ſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in the preſent truth: wee ſhall eaſily perceiue howe this may ſtop the mouthes of many, which holde blinde errors. Firſt of al of thoſe, which affirme that ignorance is the mother of deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if godlineſſe and vertue be the true deuotion, then it muſt needes folowe, that their doctrine is falſe and diueliſhe, ſeeing we are charged to ioine vnto our vertue knowledge: it is true if they mean Popiſhe deuotion, for they coulde ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="tcp:19443:24"/>
haue kept men in awe, to be zealous of their religion, and to ſeeke for that at the handes of men, which God alone doeth giue, vnleſſe they had kept them in blindneſſe and ignorance: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they tooke a wiſe way, to keepe the people from knowing the worde, which ſo ſoone as it brake foorth againe, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed all their falſhood and treacherye, in ſo muche that neither good nor bad almoſt, haue any deuotion vnto them. Secondly of thoſe, which although they bee not rancke Papiſtes, yet haue in them ſtill a ſmacke and ſauour of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh principles: and therfore like fooles, are alſo enemies vnto knowledge. For thus they ſpeake, it were no matter if there were leſſe preaching, I thinke the people bee the woorſe for it, there is knowledge euen enough, what ſhould laye men bee troubled to learne, or to ſeeke for the knoweledge of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures let them tende their woorke, and looke to their occupations, and learne to bee quiet, and to deale honeſtlye: againſt theſe poore blinde beaſtes, (for
<pb facs="tcp:19443:24"/>
I may vſe no gentle ſpeeche) wee are to reaſon out of this place: firſt that all men, knowe they neuer ſo muche, are heere commaunded to increaſe in knowledge, to the ende they may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in faith and godlineſſe. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, let them conſider to what manner of menne Saint Peter wrote, namelye, to poore and riche men, women and children, to al ſortes, and to bee ſhort, to as manie as woulde haue Faith and vertue, and ſo come to life and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, and therefore as well the poore ploughman, as the greate Clarke is commanded to increaſe his knowledge out of Gods booke: Thirdlye, they muche ouerſhoote them ſelues, when they woulde beare them in hande, that knowledge, whiche is the guider of vertue, ſhoulde bee the cauſe of vice: Naye, if wee wipe our eyes, and looke better to the matter, wee ſhall ſee, that there is a ſloodde of ignoraunce, whiche hath almoſt ouer whelmed all, and in many whiche ſeeme to know ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry muche, if they were ſounded to the
<pb facs="tcp:19443:25"/>
bottome, there ſhould be found in them groſſe ignorance, and palpable darknes: and ſo in deede the true cauſe of al foule ſinnes, which abound at this day among vs, and flowe euen as a ſwelling Sea, is the want of true knowledge. This igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce hath taken ſuch roote, that all they which haue made proofe, will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe with mee, that our time is like the time of the prophete Eſaie, 28. who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing laboured himſelfe as it were out of breathe in teaching, and ſeeing ſo ſmal profiting, beeing commaunded of the Lorde ſtil to go to his buſineſſe, bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth foorth into theſe ſpeeches: whom ſhall I teache knowledge? whome ſhall I make for to vnderſtande? them that are wained from the milke, and drawne from the breſtes? for precept muſt bee vppon precept, precept vppon precept, line vnto line, line vnto line, a litle here, and a litle there. And in an other place, hee ſaith, the woorde of the Lorde was like a ſealed booke, if hee come to o<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, ſaying, Reade this I pray you, he make<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h anſwere, I cannot reade, to another that
<pb facs="tcp:19443:25"/>
can reade, hee anſwereth, I cannot, for it is ſealed.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, let theſe ſeely creatures learne of this place to bee aſhamed of that, wherein they ſeeme after a ſorte to glorie, when they vſe to ſaye, as they thinke in defence of themſelues, wee be without ſkil, wee haue no knowledge, wee bee poore honeſt men, wee haue no learning: it is as much as to ſay, we haue no faith, we haue no vertue, wee haue no godlineſſe: for wee bee plainely taught heere that faith, vertue, and knowledge, muſt increaſe and growe vpp together. Let vs al print this leſſon deepely in our mindes, that it may driue vs to make haſte to come out of our ignorance, and to ſeeke apace after knowledge. Let vs take heede of flattering our ſelues as ſome other doe, whiche hauing gotten ſome skil, or at leaſte thinke that they haue ſette very light by the publike tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the word, they do excuſe them ſel<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es after this ſort, I thanke God, I am not of the ignorant ſorte, nor of the meaneſt iudgement, I know ſomewhat,
<pb facs="tcp:19443:26"/>
let them hunte after preaching that neede, it is very good for them, as for mee, I am ſufficiently acquainted with the matter alreadie: this kinde of men are harde too deale withall, becauſe they bee wiſe in their owne conceite, and not in the Lorde, for if they had once but euen a litle taſted of true know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge, of the ſweetneſſe and power ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, they woulde neuer haue enough of the firſt ſponeful, if they had an healthful ſtomacke, they could neuer be brought ſo ſoone to loath, &amp; as it were to vomit vp againe, ſo wholeſome ſuſtenaunce. But let vs learne heere, that when our knowledge is growne to bee neuer ſo great, becauſe we knowe but in part, and we know nothing as we ought to know, as Saynte Paule ſaith, euen then wee are to giue all diligence, to ioyne to our vertue, knowledge, vnleſſe when wee haue begunne and proceeded ſo farre, wee minde to fal backe againe. This place doth plainly ſet foorth the woeful and miſerable ſtate of thoſe whiche b<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e without teaching, or haue it in ſo ſcanty
<pb facs="tcp:19443:26"/>
a meaſure, that they come almoſt to no vnderſtanding: they are meerie and thinke all is wel, and thinke themſelues beſt, when they are leaſt dealt withall, but iudge righteous iudgement, whiche the Lorde by his Apoſtle teacheth vs to iudge, and wee ſhall ſee, that their myrth is nothing els, but a madde laughter, euen in the middeſt of feareful and horrible deſtruction. Vnto know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ioyne temperaunce, &amp;c. Or continence, for ſo the worde whiche Saint Peter vſeth, may be tranſlated. But what doth he meane, hauing bidden vs to ioyne vertue, to faith; Againe as though he had forgotten himſelf, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe certaine ſeueral kindes of vertues, which he wil haue vs to ioyne to the for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mer, when as indeed, the worde Vertue conteineth them al. We may not thinke but that hee is very wel aduiſed, and that he knoweth with whom he hath to doe, what babes and children wee are which muſt not haue meat ſet before vs in groſſe to bee our owne Caruers, but it muſt bee mynced too our handes,
<pb facs="tcp:19443:27"/>
wee muſt alſo bee fedde as it were by ſpoonfuls. For this cauſe he did not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent himſelfe to exhort in general vnto vertue, but alſo to name and pointe vs out certaine chiefe branches, which wee muſt eſpecially labour about, for vnleſſe God ſhoulde deale with vs in this wiſe, ſo vaine are wee, that we ſhould wander and roue, as it were in a wide fielde, and neuer come nigh the mark or at leaſt in looking after ſome one vertue or other, forget and let goe, the chiefe and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal. For wee ſee many that can rowle in their mouth the name of vertue and godlineſſe, and nothing almoſt but ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, vertue, as though they woulde per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade men, that their garden did growe ful of ſuch hearbes, but when wee come to this particuler examination, to looke for this vertue and that, in ſteed of theſe ſweete hearbes, wee ſhall finde nothinge but ſtinking weedes. Heere is a great parte of our diligence and wiſedome, therefore, that when wee ſtudie for ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and godlineſſe, and when we cal vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Lord for gifts, we ſearch out eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry part, and branche, leaſt wee be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeene
<pb facs="tcp:19443:27"/>
in ſome ſpecial pointe, and leaſte while wee ſeeke to increaſe one vertue, another decay in vs, for that ſhal come to paſſe, if we caſt not our eies diligently on euery ſide, and ſo oftentimes wee rather looſe then gaine, rather go back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde then forwarde. Out of the negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in this point of doctrine, or for want of knowledge in it, men grow into ſecuritie, &amp; a very litle contenteth them, yea though it be but euen ſome ſhew of vertue, and ſlouthfully they ſhuffle of the matter: a thing greatly to be taken heed vnto. Becauſe, out of al queſtion, it is that which hath cauſed diuers forwarde men, in continuance of time as it were gathering ruſt, to become ſlacke: if wee haue deſire therefore to continue, let vs learne to put this leſſon in practiſe. But why doth he wil vs to ioyne temperance or continence with knowledge, it ſhould ſeeme that he had no regarde of anie affinitie in matching theſe thinges together, for temperance is conuerſant about pleaſures and delightes: Yes verily, wee ſhal plainely ſee, that there is great cauſe for which he ioyneth eue,
<pb facs="tcp:19443:28"/>
ry one of theſe vertues together. And firſt to beginne with this, ye are to note that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinencie is not conuerſant alone, about the delights of the bodie, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of the mind: ſo that in ſeeking know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, which we muſt doe very eagerly, we are to take heede of theſe extreemes which are contrary to a contine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t mind, eyther to bee ſo wauering, that euery puffe do driue vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the manifeſt truth, or els on the other ſide to be ſo ſtiffe, &amp; ſo wilfully wedded to our owne iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that wee wil ſtande in defence of that which we haue once liked, and not admit any reaſon to the contrarie: both theſe are contrary to a continent mind: and both of them enemies to true know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge. Therefore we are warned heere in our diligent ſearche for knowledge, to take heede that when wee haue lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the truth, wee continue ſtedfaſt and vnmoueable in it, not to bee toſſed to and fro, as ſome vnſtable mindes are, who when they haue beene taught the truthe, the leaſt doubt that is raiſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, cauſeth them by &amp; by to ſhake,
<pb facs="tcp:19443:28"/>
&amp; to feare whether they be in the righte way or no, alſo wee muſt take heede of that ſtiffeneſſe, which cauſeth ſome to ſpeake when it were better for them too heare: &amp; to be heard aloft, when a lower voyce might ſerue them better: far from the counſel of S. Iames who willeth vs to be ſwift to heare, and ſlow to ſpeake. Let vs be ſure our knowledge be wel groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, before we ſetle our ſelues to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newe in it: leaſt in ſteede of heaping vp golde, wee fil our cheſts with nothing but droſſe. Alſo wee muſt beware, that wee bend our ſtudie for the knowledge of theſe pointes which ſerue to increaſe godlines, and true edifying. For many ſeeke for knowledge, but their vayne braine, doth carie them to ſeeke after curious queſtions, and too let paſſe thoſe thinges, which ſhoulde doe them moſt good: and this is a ſore and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous ſickneſſe in men, as the queſtions they commonly moue, doe ſhewe. Hee addeth, To temperance ioyne patience. This alſo may ſeeme to bee ſomewhat ſtrange, but if wee looke well vnto it,
<pb facs="tcp:19443:29"/>
we then ſhal perceiue the meaning more plainely: patience is not only requiſite in thoſe which haue receiued the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Goſpel, to beare and indure al perſecutions &amp; afflictions, which of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes are ſo raging, that (except wee haue our hartes wel ſtaied, and ſeaſoned with patience) wee ſhal be driuen to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake, and to forſwere our knoweledge: but alſo it is very requiſite to be wel ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and fenced with it, when we ſhal haue to do with thoſe which are abſurd and groſſe, and therefore it is as a dag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to a mans hearte, to heare al their blockiſh reaſons againſt the worde, to ſee howe ſenſeleſſe they are, when the plaine truth is laide before them: Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe their ſpiteful raylinges, and fleeting mockes, which they will vſe: their bolde abuſing of Gods worde, their arrogant preſumption, which cauſeth them to prattle very faſt, euen they knowe not what: or eles wee ſhall be hurled hither and thither vpon rockes, and make ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke of our mildeneſſe: and ſo marre and diſgrace the good cauſe, which wee haue in hande. For wicked men will
<pb facs="tcp:19443:29"/>
iudge al to proceed of rancour &amp; anger, and aſcribe all to choller, and ſo by this meanes there is procured ſome diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor to God: who ſhould greatly be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nored if we could meekely (as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle willeth) inſtruct thoſe which are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie minded, proouing if God at any time wil giue them repentance, to come out of the ſnare of the Diuel of whome they be holden captiue, to do his wil: &amp; ſo to ſtop their mouthes, that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be able to anſwere. The want of this vertue oftentimes bringeth greate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conuenience, to the conference of bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, which ſhould bring togither (as it were into one heape) whatſoeuer euery one hath gleaned by himſelf, that ſo the one might ſupply the want of the other: but the impatience of ſome is ſuch, that great inconuenience doth growe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by. To conclude this matter, ſeing trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles are alotted vnto vs, &amp; ſufferings for the truth, &amp; that we are ſubiect to ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reproches, railings, taunts, &amp; mocks, at the hands of abſurd &amp; euil men: who ſoeuer looketh to walke in the way of knowledge, he muſt ſeeke to poſſeſſe his
<pb facs="tcp:19443:30"/>
ſoule in patience. It folowith, with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence godlines, &amp;c. A man may demand what maner of order is here vſed, in wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling vs to ioyne godlines to patience, &amp; then to godlines, brotherly kindneſſe: is not godlines the whole or the general, &amp; theſe bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ches, are members of it? True it is that this worde is often vſed, gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally to comprehende al goodneſſe, but in this place, it comprehendeth but the firſt table of the lawe, wherein wee are willed to bee deuout or zealous: a very neceſſarie caueat to beware that we doe not become ſo patient, that we forget to be zealous in the Lords quarrel: it is as if Saint Peter ſhould haue ſaid: I woulde not haue you ſo meeke, as to beare and put vp al, I woulde haue you withal to bee hotte in Gods quarrell, forget not that. For many vnder a colour of a meeke patience, doe couer the want of religion, for if God bee diſhonored, his trueth defaced, his ſeruants ſlaundered, they can heare and ſee, and yet bee as meeke as a Lambe: but if themſelues bee touched yee ſhal ſee them playe the Lions, and of luke warme to become
<pb facs="tcp:19443:30"/>
fire hot, this therefore is no patience which wanteth godlineſſe. Wee muſt learne then, both with patience, and meeknes, to deale in the Lords matters, &amp; alſo with feruent zeale: leaſt in ſteed of this excellent vertue of patience, which was commended vnto vs, there be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a prophane vngodlines &amp; an irreligious mildneſſe, in which at this day moe do offend, then through impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience: for theſe Athieſts haue this as an excuſe very readily. Are we not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be gentle and ſoft? Is it not our duetie to maintaine loue, and charitie with our neighbours? Indeede they bee great ſwearers, and ſomtime they vſe to ſpeake againſt gods worde, if they be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wry, I think they ſhal anſwere for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, if we ſhould gaineſay, or ſeeme to reprooue them, they woulde not take it wel, therefore I thinke good not to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet them. Heere is nowe wonderfull patience, theſe are verye godlye and charitable perſons, yea euen a treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie towardes GOD and men. For is there any of them, which being ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered with ſome foule crime, whereby
<pb facs="tcp:19443:31"/>
they ſhould receiue great iniurie, or bee ſpitefully rayled vppon, if ſome of their neere friendes ſitte by and holde their tongues, when they know they be iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, that cannot by and by feele &amp; ſay, this was cold friendſhip, that they could not haue dealt ſo vnlouingly towardes their friendes, by whome ſoeuer they ſhould haue heard them ſo abuſed, they could not haue held their tongues? The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> belike God nor his truth are none of their deare friends, that they can put vp ſuch iniurie done towards him. There is plentie of this patience in all places, but godlineſſe cannot bee ſuffered to come neere, for he is a breake peace and a very vnpleaſant felow, hee is ouer rough and preciſe, and ouer captious, there was good neighbourhood and friendſhippe before he came, they could be merie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and bee in vnitie, without anye iarre: had it not bene better to vſe gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleneſſe and patience, then to haue this broyle? for there is nothing better then loue, and where that is not, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing good. O miſerable daies! this is the good loue now amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that they
<pb facs="tcp:19443:31"/>
cannot loue one another, but they muſt hate God, to haue peace and concorde with men to bee at ods with God, for mens ſake, to put vp the diſhonoring of his name, not to continue in patience, vnleſſe godlineſſe bee wanting. The vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly world, and lewde nature that is in men, taketh occaſion to accuſe godly zeale, vnder this pretence: and to finde fault with the preaching of the worde, becauſe, ſay they, it ſetteth men at ſtrife. But we muſt learne in this place to ioine godlineſſe with our patience, for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe we ſhalbe found to be nothing els but irreligious and prophane dogges: although wee pretende loue neuer ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much. The time wil not ſuffer to handle the reſt, which remaineth in this text. Let vs remember that which hath beene ſaid, &amp; giue all diligence to purſue theſe excellent vertues, that ſo wee may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue our ſelues to be right Chriſtians, and looke for the bleſſed hope promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in Ieſu Chriſt.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:19443:32"/>
            <head>The third Sermon.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7</hi> And with godlines, brotherly kindnes, and with brotherly kindnes, loue.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8</hi> For if theſe things be with you and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound, they will make you that ye ſhal not be idle, nor vnfruitful, in the knowledge of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <hi>9</hi> For he that hath not theſe thinges it blind and ſeeth not a farre of, and hath forgotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that he was purged from his olde ſinnes.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>ANd with godlineſſe brotherly kindnes,</hi> &amp;c. Wee haue heard already, that with our faith muſt be ioyned vertue or godly deedes, which it cannot be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, if it be a true faith: with vertue wee are commaunded to ioyne knowledge, which may bee a guide thereunto, our knowledge muſt goe with temperance, with this muſt come patience, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto muſt be ioined godlines. There re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine yet two branches of theſe ſpecial vertues, about which wee are to trauell: the firſt of theſe is brotherly loue or
<pb facs="tcp:19443:32"/>
kindeneſſe, which muſt be yoked with godlines: as I ſaid, that this godlines he ſpeaketh of, is referred to the firſt table of the law, reſpecting God and his reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, that wee bee ſound and zelous in the ſame, and not as thoſe which are for al times, and al religions, and therefore care not what bee ſaide againſt religion, beeing very belliegods and Atheiſts: ſo this is referred to the ſeconde table, ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing what wee owe vnto men. This is very fitly, and neceſſarily added, for as there bee many, which regarding men onely, howe to pleaſe, and not to grieue or offende them, altogether forgetting their dutie towards the Lord God, and wholy ſhutting him out, as thogh their chief care ſhould be of men, let pas god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines: ſo there bee ſome that offend on the other ſide, which looking alwaies ſo high, as to haue reſpect to the Lord, and his trueth, to bee earneſt and firie in that, ouerlooke men, forgetting the dueties which they owe vnto them: the holye Apoſtle meeteth with this miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, and telleth vs that we muſt ſo loue God, that we alſo loue men: ioyne, ſaith
<pb facs="tcp:19443:33"/>
hee, to your godlineſſe, brotherly kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: for vnleſſe this be ioyned, and goe with our zeale of Gods worde, it is no true godlineſſe, although wee bee neuer ſo ſounde in iudgement and ſeeme to be as hotte as Moyſes or Elias, yea euen to be ſwallowed vp with burning zeale: for it doeth not proceede from Gods ſpirite, who doeth alſo worke the loue towardes men whereſoeuer hee goeth: but it doeth proceede of ſome corrupt cauſe, as of vaineglorie, or ſelfe loue, and ſuch like, and deſerueth not indeede tobee called godly deuotion, no more then the true faith can be without ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, or deſerueth to be called ought, ſaue a ſhadowe, or Image of faith, if it bee without good workes: but it is a bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which reſembleth the true zeale, which doth euermore carrie with it, a loue, and care towardes men. True it is that to be zealous in ſpirite, is a ſingular and ſpeciall gift of God, and they which be without it are but brutiſh, &amp; ſenſleſſe creatures, not knowing God, nor howe precious his glory is: yet this muſt be lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed vnto in euerie one of vs, whether we
<pb facs="tcp:19443:33"/>
beare a lo<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing affection toward our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren or no: for if we loue God, we muſt needs loue men, which beare his Image. If we delight in the worde of God, this is one chiefe point of doctrine which is taught in it, that we be louing and kind vnto men. Therefore as Saint Paule 1. Cor. 13. ſheweth, that very excellent giftes doe not profite without loue, ſo likewiſe in this place wee be taught, that if wee woulde ſeeme to bee godly, and haue not loue, it is nothing worth. Let euery man therefore lay this doctrine to his hearte: that hee muſt be earneſt in the cauſes of the Lorde, zealous in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, preferring God and his truth, before all men, whoſoeuer, and whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer they be: but yet withal that he muſt looke downe vnto men, rendring vnto them their due alſo, this doing hee may beholde hee is in the right way. Vnto this brotherly loue wee bee charged to ioyne loue. It may bee heere deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againe, what manner of ſpeeche this is, which the Apoſtle doeth vſe, for is not brotherly kindneſſe or brotherly
<pb facs="tcp:19443:34"/>
loue, as the word doth ſignifie, and loue al one; We muſt bee farre from thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Saint Peter to deale with ſo little heede, as to wil vs to ioyne the very ſame thing to the ſame: wee muſt therefore ſeeke a difference betweene theſe two. We may take this difference, either that the firſt of theſe doth expreſſe what wee owe towards the Godly, who be chiefly called the brethren, and the latter what we owe vnto all, both good and bad: or els the former, doth ſignifie the inwarde affection of loue, and the latter, the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward practiſe of the ſame: for the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine in both theſe, is needful to be ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. If we take then the former ſenſe, we be willed to ioine with our loue towards the godly and faithful brethren (whom we ought chiefly, and more dearely to fauour,) a loue alſo which may reache euen ouer al, good and bad, friend and foe, This Saint Paule teacheth when he willeth vs to do good to all men, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which are of the houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde of faith. So that we muſt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge our ſelues bounde, in ſome ſort, euen to the wicked: according as our
<pb facs="tcp:19443:34"/>
Sauiour doth teach, Math. 5. Bleſſe them which curſe you, pray for them whiche hate and perſecute you: and Saint Paul ſaith, Rom. 12. If thine enemie hunger, feede him: if he thirſt, giue him drinke. Well then, although this bee very harde to mans nature, yet the Lorde doeth ſtreightly require it at our hands: and ſo that if this bee wanting, wee doe but deceiue our ſelues. If we take it in the latter ſenſe, the firſt worde to ſignifie the inward affection of loue, the other, the outward practiſe: then we haue heere a notable point to be obſerued, not to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſhoote our ſelues in our loue, in iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging it to be right, &amp; ſincere, when it is halting, and lame: for many when they heare, that we are ſo ſtraightly charged, for to loue our neighbours, &amp; that with out the ſame, there is nothing good in vs, or which God accepteth: looke no further but thus, whether they bear any grudge or euil wil in their mindes, &amp; if they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſay I hurt no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor I meane no hurt to any, they perſuade the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues that this is an excellent loue. And ſo a ſtone
<pb facs="tcp:19443:35"/>
meaning no hurt may bee ſaide to loue: other ſomwhat wiſer, do not only looke to that one thing, whether they beare euil will, but alſo whether they haue any kind of affection in them, and here they ſtay, when they ſhoulde goeyet this ſtep further, to ſee that this kindnes in them, breaketh foorth into good and charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble deeds: for there may be ſome louing affection in a man, and yet bring foorth but ſle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der fruits, bicauſe there is a great ſlouth in nature, which hindreth men from putting their loue in vre, for loue is labourſome and paineful as Saint Paule ſetteth it forth 1. Theſ. 1. when he ſaith, Your laboring loue. If then we wil loue the brethren, heere is the touchſtone, by which we may proue our loue, that wee ſpare not for any labour or coſt, nor yet waxe weery: becauſe loue is not like one that is lazie &amp; luskiſh, loytring at home within a mans breſt, but ſteppeth abrod and is verie diligent: neither doeth it preferre euery light commodity &amp; vaine pleaſure, before the benefite of the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren. Then by this it is manifeſt, how
<pb facs="tcp:19443:35"/>
that al thoſe which would ſeeme to bee godly, and yet haue caſt away the care o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer their brethren, at the leaſt thus farre, that they wil neither trauel, nor be at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny charge, for other mens ſake: whoſe wealth they ſhold procure, eſpecially of the ſoule, for therein lieth the chiefe tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al of loue: becauſe it is a prepoſterous thing, to be very tender ouer the bodie, a rotten carkaſſe, and to pitie the miſerie thereof ſo much, &amp; in the meane while, not to care for that, that is more preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, namely the ſoule, the relieuing and healing of which, ſhal be the happineſſe of the whole man for euer. This I ſpeake becauſe wee ſee many, that wil beſtowe ſomewhat vpon the reliefe of the bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly miſerie, which haue no pitie vpon mé, which wander in blindnes &amp; ignorance, whoſe ſoules are famiſhed &amp; pined, for want of foode, full of deadly woundes and ſores, which are not ſalued, bounde in the bands, and chaines of ſinne, hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den vnder captiuitie by Satan, euen rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to be ſwallowed vp, of the bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe gulfe of hell: the cauſe in deede is,
<pb facs="tcp:19443:36"/>
that they haue not yet learned to pitie their owne ſoules, and therefore cannot pitie the ſoules of their brethren: for if they did know the ſpiritual miſerie, they woulde neither ſpare night nor day in trauelling to haue it eaſed: wheras now contrariwiſe they can pull backe men, from godlineſſe, and diſcourage them from ſeeking after ſaluation: they can laugh &amp; ſport themſelues in their owne ſinnes, and in the ſinnes of their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, as though there were no miſerie therein, finally, being cruel murtherers of ſoules, would neuertheles, gladly be deemed charitable: But their bountifull almes, doth want ſeaſoning. Let vs learn therefore to pitie, &amp; to ſhewe kindnes to the bodily neceſſitie of men, and not to forget eſpecially, &amp; aboue al, to procure with al diligence, as much as lyeth in vs, the ſaluation of their ſoules: otherwiſe we can neuer be ſaide to ioyne loue, and godlineſſe together.</p>
            <p>In that which followeth in the foure nexte verſes, there is ſhewed partly the great, and ſingular commodities, which
<pb facs="tcp:19443:36"/>
wee ſhal reape, if wee bee garniſhed with theſe foreſaide vertues: and partly the diſcommodities, which we ſhal finde, in the want of the ſame. And this S. Peter ſetteth forth, not ſtaying in the bare de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the vertues, which indeed of themſelues, beeing ſo precious &amp; excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſhoulde moue vs, but dealeth with vs, as with thoſe which are lumpiſh, and dul, needing many ſpurres, to bee pric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked forwarde withall, and all litle e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough: let vs bee careful therefore to take heede to that hee ſaieth. If theſe things be with you, &amp; abound, they will make, &amp;c. In this 8. verſe, hee beginneth to ſhew the commodities which ſhal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dounde vnto vs, if wee ſo giue our dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, that wee may bee richly decked with theſe graces: they wil make you, ſaith the Apoſtle, that yee ſhal not bee idle, nor vnfruiteful, in the acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſte. It is a ſhameful thing, when GOD hath ſhewed himſelfe vnto vs in his Sonne, hath called vs into his ſeruice, out of miſerable bondage, for vs to bee ydle, and vnfruiteful: If the Lorde haue
<pb facs="tcp:19443:37"/>
planted vs, if he haue dreſſed vs, then, as it is alſo ſaid by our ſauiour Chriſt, Iohn 15. Herein is my father glorified, that ye goe and bring foorth much fruite. Then it is by this place very apparant, that a man may draw out a ſure &amp; an infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible argument, againſt all thoſe whiche are idle, and ſlouthful in the profeſſion of religion, and as they ſay key colde, or ſlack in the worſhip, &amp; ſeruice of god, or vnfruitful in good workes: namely, that they are graceles, voide of faith &amp; thoſe vertues which doe euer accompany the ſame: for when Saint Peter ſaith, if theſe things bee with you, they wil make that ye ſhal not be idle, nor vnfruitful, it fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth neceſſarily, that ſuch as bee idle, which ariſeth for want of zeale, or bee vnfruitful, continuing in their ſinnes, it is, becauſe they did neuer yet come to the true knowledge of Ch<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſt; they may wel boſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, of their ſtrong faith, make a braue ſhewe of their skil, &amp; ſine wit, ſo that men might think there were ſome deepe thing in them, &amp; that they ſhold be able eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to iudge, &amp; giue aright verdit, in al matters: but a man reading
<pb facs="tcp:19443:37"/>
but euen this place, finding them ydle, and vnfruitful, (yea euen a ſimple man) ſhal eaſily ſounde them to the bottome, and ſay of them, that they haue not as yet knowne or learned Chriſte: becauſe they want thoſe former thinges. Wee muſt note this alſo, when hee ſaith, If theſe thinges abounde in you: this is, that wee ſhould not content our ſelues, with a ſcant and bare meaſure of faith, of vertue, of knowledge, and of the reſt, as he ſetteth them downe: but we muſt labour to haue a dayly increaſe, for that muſt bee gathered by this, that he pric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth forwarde theſe ripe, and grounded men. A doctrine moſt neceſſary to be vrged, becauſe if men haue gone two, or three ſteppes, or haue once a litle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunne, to labour about theſe thinges, ſo that they can looke backe, and ſee ſome come behinde them, or can ſay I thanke God, I knowe ſomewhat. I hope that I am not without faith, ſomewhat there is which I haue done, that I would be loth to doe againe: they by and by perſuade themſelues, that they are ſufficiently fur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſhed; ſo that they wil not ſticke to ſay,
<pb facs="tcp:19443:38"/>
I truſt I haue that which ſhall ſerue the turne. Naye, the Apoſtle telleth vs an other thing heere from the Lord, &amp; that is, that we muſt ouerflow in theſe, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounde: and truth it is, that theſe men which thinke they bee well fraught, and ſo ſeeke for no further increaſe of ſtore, haue as yet nothing, for if they had once founde the ſweete of theſe thinges, and ſeene withall that they are farre behind, and in beggerly need, they would neuer content themſelues with ſo little: for who is hee, which feeleth increaſe in worldlye treaſure, that wil crie hoe, and ſay, I haue enough? Is there leſſe in the heauenly treaſures to drawe men to like them, than in the earthy? Or is it becauſe men doe not knowe them? Wee muſt learne to take heede of ſuch there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as woulde beare men in hande, that it is ſufficient, yea, that it is the beſt of al, for men to content the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues with ſome ciuil honeſtie, and not to ſeeke and wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie their mindes to gaine knowledge. But theſe were neuer as yet the men, which might bee right called the ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of Chriſte, much leſſe wee are to
<pb facs="tcp:19443:38"/>
deeme them worthie maſters, or tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of others, when they goe flat con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the holy Apoſtle of Chriſte, who willeth to ſeek for ſo great abundance: when as they would conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t themſelues and perſuade others to bee contented, with ſcant a ſhadowe of theſe thinges, which ſhoulde bee ſo plentifully founde in them: Notwithſtanding ſome are ſo blinde, that hauing no ſhadow or ſhewe at al of goodneſſe, yet thinke they bee gone farre enough. In the next verſe where hee ſaith, Hee that hath not theſe thinges, is blinde, and ſeeth not a farre of, and hath forgotten that he was purged from his olde ſinnes: hee ſetteth forth the diſcommodities which follow the want of theſe vertues. And this hee doth, becauſe ſome man wil be litle mooued to heare that commoditie which hee ſpake of, and wil ſay, what care I though I bee idle? What care I though I bee vnfruitful? I will not goe about to be better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other men, what ſhould I labour to excel thoſe which are wiſer then I; If then they wil not regard this, that theſe vertues wil make them
<pb facs="tcp:19443:39"/>
excellent ſeruants of God, yet let them conſider what the Apoſtle maketh them without the ſame, where hee affirmeth them firſt to bee blinde, (a very miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thing in the bodily ſight, muche more in the ſpirituall, which hee here meaneth:) when God hath ſo cleerely reuealed himſelf in the face of his ſonne, in the knowledge which bringeth ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, that the God of this worlde, as Saint Paule ſpeaketh. 2. Cor. 4. ſhould ſo blinde their minds, that the light of the glorious Goſpel of Chriſte, which is the image of God, ſhoulde not ſhine vnto them. Secondly he ſaith, they cannot ſee a farre of, or that they be poreblinde, for ſuch as haue the beames of ſight ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring or ſpreading a ſunder, ſo ſoone as they be out of the eye, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſee wel enough iuſt by them, but not a farre of, to theſe S. Peter doth compare thoſe men. But it may be asked what he meaneth: firſt to ſay they be ſtarke blinde, &amp; afterward to attribute ſome ſight vnto them. It may ſeeme by this worde, that hee ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth their cauſe not ſo euil, as before he had ſaide it was: yes euen as euill, for he
<pb facs="tcp:19443:39"/>
ſaith as much in this worde, as he did in the other: for when he ſaith, They can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee a farre of, hee taketh from them al ſight of heauenly thinges, which are remoued from vs, &amp; ſeene only by faith: hee doeth not denie them the ſight of thoſe things which are at hand, becauſe they haue a good and a ſharpe ſight in the thinges of this worlde, for the moſt part, better then they which can ſee a far of. But what are theſe quicke wits the better, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are but for this world, and their condition no better then that of the poore beaſt, (yea muche worſe) when we reſpect the miſery in the world to come? Let not this therfore cauſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſet vp their briſtles, that they can ſee ſo wel and pearcingly at hande, (that is, in earthly thinges) when as they are as blinde as beetles in things a far of, that is to ſay, in heauenly things. Heere wee muſt ſeeke to haue eyes giuen vs of god, with which wee may bee able to ſee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yonde this worlde: for before ſuch time as the Lorde hath giuen vs ſome glim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mering of heauenly things, wee ſhal ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer couet to obteine them. And this is
<pb facs="tcp:19443:40"/>
the cauſe that theſe poreblinde men ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer paſſe greatly to know the Goſpel of Chriſte. Thirdly he ſaith, they haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that they were purged from their olde ſinnes: as hee ſaid they were blind, ſo nowe he ſaith, they are forgetful: and this forgetfulneſſe is ſo much the more ſhameful, as it is in a chiefe &amp; principal point of true religion. But where ſhall wee find the man, which if he be exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned will confeſſe that he hath forgotten this point? It ſeemeth none doe forget it, becauſe the very wicked will ſeeme to ſet al vpon this ſcore, that their ſins are purged, and that maketh them ſinne ſo franckly. But if we vnderſtande the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle wel, we ſhall finde very many whiche haue forgotten this point. Now here we muſt firſt note that our ſinnes are ſaid to bee purged, when there is ſatisfaction made for them by redemption in the blood of Chriſte.</p>
            <p>Secondly that they are ſaid to be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by grace of ſanctification, when by the power of Gods ſpirite, ſinne, or all ſinfull affections are ſuppreſſed and kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in vs: ſo then there is a purging in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption,
<pb facs="tcp:19443:40"/>
and there is alſo a purging by ſanctification: Nowe if they haue not forgotten ſo much, but that they can prattle of the purging of their ſins, by redemption, yet they haue forgotten this, that they were redeemed to the ende they ſhoulde no longer ſerue ſinne but purge away the olde leauen: But beeing without thoſe former graces, he ſayeth they haue forgotten this, not meaning thereby that they had euer learned it, for if they had, yet at the leaſt they had not wel learned it: wee may ſee by this howe many there bee, which are ſtarke blinde, and haue forgotten that Chriſtians are called to liue in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe and holineſſe of life. If we looke vpon the ſmall number of thoſe which haue a care to ſeeke after the Lord, and howe ſmall a parte of them doe come (I will not ſaye to abounde,) but to haue a competent meaſure of thoſe forenamed vertues. Let vs come al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to this true meaſure, and not bee deceiued neither in our ſelues, nor in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Let vs bee aſhamed if we be carnal, to take vppon vs the name of the true
<pb facs="tcp:19443:41"/>
profeſſours: let vs denie vnto them the honorable name of Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, which are but filthie ſwine, and prophane dogges, as our Sauiour Chriſte calleth them: to conclude this matter, none are allowed to bee true receiuers of the Goſpel, but ſuch as ioyne vertue with their faith, &amp; with vertue knowledge, and ſo tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, patience, godlineſſe, brotherly kindenes, and loue, and ſuch as alſo doe ſeeke to abound in them: the reſt which care not for theſe, or conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t themſelues with the bare ſhewe of them, although they would ſeeme to be worſhippers of God, and deuout perſons, yet they are by this doctrine of the Lord wholy ſhut foorth, vntill they haue learned a newe leſſon. Remember that this is the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of God, and not of man. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that we muſt ſtand and dwell vppon it, not for a day, or two, while wee haue hearde it, but all our life long to bring it to the practiſe, it is plaine and cleere, none can be excuſed if they know it not and ſo through ſimplicitie ſtand vppon the common faith, thinking to ſhroude themſelues wel vnder the ſhadow of the
<pb facs="tcp:19443:41"/>
multitude: but when God hath warned them, who wil pitie them, when they wil not be warned; if this were not told vs, and that by God him ſelfe, wee might thinke, as men doe commonly, that a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry little doth content the Lord, that no great things are required at the handes of Chriſtians, and other ſuch fooliſh, and vaine opinions, as to ſay, they muſt hope wel when God telleth them, there is no hope, vnleſſe they walke this way, alſo that it is not good to bee ouer preciſe, when as in goodnes a man cannot pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede too far, nor offer too muche obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Lorde. To make an ende, let none of al theſe thinges blinde vs, becauſe they blinde ſome, which ſtande in reputation of their owne wiſdome.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:19443:42"/>
            <head>The fourth Sermon.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p n="10">
                     <hi>10</hi> Wherefore brethren, giue rather dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to make your calling &amp; ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction ſure: for if ye do theſe things yee ſhall neuer fall.</p>
                  <p n="11">
                     <hi>11</hi> For by this meanes an entring ſhall be miniſtred vnto you abundantly, in to the euerlaſting kingdom of our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>JT hath beene tolde vnto you already, vppon the verſes which goe next be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, howe that Saint Peter regarding how dull wee are and backward in god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, contented not himſelfe with his exhortation which he maketh, but ſetteth downe what we ſhall gaine if we follow his aduiſe, and alſo what hurt we ſhall ſuſtaine by the contrary: and this hath partly been handeled in the two o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther verſes, &amp; partly in theſe two which wee haue now in hand: where indeed he doth propounde ſo great a commodity which we ſhal gaine, if wee giue all dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence
<pb facs="tcp:19443:42"/>
to purſue the former things, as is almoſt incomparable: euen this, that we ſhal come to the aſſurance, that wee are called &amp; choſen of God: a thing ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for vs to knowe, that without it, there is no right faith, no frank and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling obedience, no ſounde ioy. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though without this, men ſeeme to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, yet is it but a wauering fantaſie, to do many good things, yet they proceed but from a ſeruile minde, to laugh &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce, yet is it but in a deſperate madnes which in very deed is greatly to be won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered at, howe men ſhoulde bee able to ſport themſelues, &amp; yet to ſpeak in their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences after this maner, there is hel, and eternal flames of vengeance prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for ſinners, and I am not ſure whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I ſhal eſcape or not: this deſperate and brutiſh ſecuritie ſhalbe apparant to bee the more mad, if wee compare it, and ſet it foorth by an outward compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon. Let it bee thus, a man is taken in a robberie or murther, impriſoned, brought before the Iudge, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, by ſute of friendes repriued vntil ſuche time as they maye ſue for
<pb facs="tcp:19443:43"/>
to get him a pardon: in the meane time ſome of his acquaintance come to this murtherer, and will him to be of good cheere, &amp; merie, he wil anſwere, vnleſſe he be ſome mad and deſperate ruffian, I am condemned to the Gallowes, the Iudge hath pronounced the ſentence of death vpon mee, I know not how harde a thing it wil bee to obteine a pardon, I ſtand in great doubt, and for this cauſe I cannot bee merie, vnleſſe I myghte know for certaintie that I ſhould eſcape, if I did once know that, I coulde bee as mery as any man that liueth, before that tyme I may ſeeme to laughe, but my hearte is full of feare and ſorrowe. And is it not thus with vs all, are wee not all of vs giltie, and alreadie condemned by the ſentence of the higheſt Iudge; not to ſome torment of one day, or ſhorte continuance, but to the fire that ſhal ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be quenched? When men can be merie therefore and laugh euen in thoſe things which cauſe this deſtruction, and yet doe feele that they are not ſure to eſcape this dreadfull vengeance, is it not a mad mirth and a deſperate laughter,
<pb facs="tcp:19443:43"/>
in which if they were not become verye ſenſles blockes, they ſhoulde feele many gripings at the hart, which would marre al their myrth, yea a worme that gnaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in ſuche wiſe, that they can haue no quiet reſt, nor as I ſaid before no ſound ioy. If we were not therfore more then deſperate and mad fooles, the thought of hel would dampe al our mirth vntyl ſuch time as we be ſure that we haue eſca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ped it. This then which the Apoſtle ſaith heere is a princely commoditie, that walking the way which he hath preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, we ſhall come to the aſſurance, that wee are the called and choſen of the Lord. But it may be demanded how this can agree with other ſayings in the holy ſcriptures, which doe plainly teach that God choſeth whom he will of his owne free grace, for which S. Paule alleadgeth out of Moſes, that God will haue mercy on whomſoeuer he wil haue mercy, and whom he wil he hardeneth: adding ther upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that it is neither of him that willeth nor yet of him that runneth, but of god which ſheweth mercy: againe the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of Popery is, that God doth make
<pb facs="tcp:19443:44"/>
choiſe, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditionally reſpecting the good deeds which he did foreſee in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: &amp; ſo the election ſhold depend vpon the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thines of the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: we are to anſwere that this place hath nothing in it whiche is contrary to that free choiſe which God maketh without reſpect of any thinge that is in vs, for he could finde nothing in vs that might any way moue him, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth it ſerue at al for to proue that election is conditional: becauſe S. Peter doth not handle in this place, wherevp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on election is founded, or what moued god to make choiſe, nor to ſhew wherin the certaintie &amp; ſtableneſſe of election doth ſtand: but his meaning is, to teach vs how we ſhal attaine to this incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable treaſure, to bee out of doubt, and ſurely reſolued in our ſelues, not by fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſied opinions, but by ſure &amp; ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tial proofe, that we be choſen of God, and therfore cannot periſh. If we reſpect the vnchangeable counſel of God, therein doth reſt alone the ſure foundation of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, becauſe God which cannot bee deceiued, nor cannot repent, or change, hath made the choiſe, therefore thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:19443:44"/>
whom he hath choſen, can neuer periſht but if we regard the way and meanes, by which we may come to know this fauor of God to be toward vs, the Lord by his apoſtle telleth vs, that this is the way, euen to giue al diligence &amp; ſtudy, to be richly decked with his graces, or thoſe forena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vertues, for by theſe wee ſhall vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly know, becauſe if we haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if they abound in vs, if we walk in them, we ſhal, as he ſaith, neuer fal. Let vs learn therefore firſt this, that election in it ſelf reſteth vpon the vnchangeable purpoſe &amp; counſel of God. Then ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly that we are not to fetch the certentie of it in our ſelues, from ſom reuelation, neither are we to clime vp into heauen, to ſearch in the counſels of god, whether our names be in the book of life. But we are to fetch our warrant from within our ſelues, and that from the fruits of the ſpirite, which indeed although it be out of our ſelues, yet becauſe it is not of our ſelues, is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain &amp; infallible. If ye wil vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d this more plainely, firſt I ſay, it is out of our ſelues, or from within our ſelues becauſe wee muſt take the triall, whether thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:19443:45"/>
thinges bee in vs, which are giuen to al thoſe whome God doeth chooſe, then I ſay it is not of our ſelues, for if it were, it ſhould be altogether vncertaine. But of the ſeale of God wherwith he hath ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vs, which is the ſpirite of ſanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: now mark wel I pray you, If you do, (ſaith S. Peter) theſe thinges, you ſhal ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer fal: and why, is it becauſe our doings are ſo perfect and ſure, or that we are ſo conſtant of our ſelues; no not ſo, but by theſe vertues we know that we are ſealed with Gods ſpirite, whoſe woorke wee feele in vs: wee know alſo that as many as are led by the ſpirite of God are the ſonnes of God. Rom. 8. From hence it commeth, that looke howe muche more a man feeleth in him ſelfe the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of knowledge, the increaſe of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues and heauenly deſires, ſo muche more ſure hee is, that hee is the childe of God, and as the one increaſeth, ſo increaſeth alſo the other. Contrariwiſe when a man feeleth within him ſelfe an euil conſcience, feeleth that he is darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in his vnderſtanding, ledde by the luſtes of ſinne: hee ſhall in ſpite of his
<pb facs="tcp:19443:45"/>
teeth within himſelfe, ſing this dolefull ſong, I knowe not whether I ſhal bee ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued or not: and looke howe the other may ſay I knowe I ſhal be ſaued, becauſe God hath ſealed me with his ſpirite: ſo may this ſay, I am ſure to bee damned continuing in this caſe, becauſe I haue not faith, but onely a wauering and doubtfull opinion. We may ſee by this how beneficial they are, and merciful to their owne ſoules, which with al their power day &amp; night giue vp themſelues to ſeek after the knowledge and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the Lords wil: for not giuing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, nor waxing wearie, they ſhal in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of time, if they ply it hard, find ſuch a bleſſing from the Lord, in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of faith and vertue, that wil cauſe them to ſay, we haue not loſt our labor. On the other ſide wee may ſee howe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde and cruel they are to themſelues, which through idlenes, &amp; ſlouth, in ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king after God, with their daily and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual ſinnes, doe euen as it were cut the throte of their faith, ſeeing they cannot haue truſte in him, whome they doe ſo much diſobey. This place is as a mightie
<pb facs="tcp:19443:46"/>
engine to ouerthrow the vanitie of ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie opinions which doe reigne in men. As firſt of al in thoſe whiche crie out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this doctrine, as a thing which wil make men careleſſe and idle in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of God, and ſtoppe the courſe of good woorkes, I beſeech you marke how wel theſe great wiſe men haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited in Gods ſchoole, ſee howe they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with the holy Apoſtle, he ſaith wee are to giue al our ſtudie and diligence in good woorkes to come to the ſure and vndoubted knowledge, that we be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen vnto life: they ſay quite contrary, if ye wil haue men careful of wel doing, away with the doctrine of election, for it will marre al: thus the wiſedome of fleſhe doth proudly lift vp it ſelfe euen againſt God (but howe fooliſhly, a very child may ſee:) Doeth that thing which wee cannot come to the knowledge of, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exceeding care of godlineſſe, abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of vertue, and plentie of all good woorkes, deſtroy in men the ſtudie and care of good workes? But proud fleſhe is worthily blind. Some other, although not thus bruitiſhly blinded, yet greatly
<pb facs="tcp:19443:46"/>
ouerſeene, when they thinke on this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, which is ſet vp vnto vs as the mark for vs to aime at in al our doings, and the trial whether we haue done wel or not: I meane the trial in this reſpecte, and when a man hath done many good deedes, hee ſhal know he hath not done them wel, if hee yet doubt, whether hee bee one of Gods choſen, for howſoeuer hee paſſeth it ouer, yet his conſcience (which doth in ſome ſort know, that he hath not dealt but for vaine glory, or ſome other ſiniſter reſpect) wil not ſuffer him to haue this faith: For God doth not woorke ſo darkely by his ſpirite in men, but that they may learne to knowe whether it bee of him, if they woulde make a due triall: becauſe wee muſt not reſt in the outwarde doeing of good thinges, but in the right doing. Let him therefore whiche giueth him ſelfe to doe good woorkes, (and yet fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth not this, which Saint Peter ſaith, we ſhal) ſuſpect that his doinges are miſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, and be careful to faſhion them after the rules of the worde. A thirde ſort
<pb facs="tcp:19443:47"/>
of men there be, which with might and maine wil defende this doctrine, that men ought to be ſure of ſaluation, that wee cannot more honour God, then to giue ful credite to his promiſes, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the plaine teſtimonie of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture compelleth them, they affirme it conſtantly, and condemne the contrary as a foule errour, that God hath choſen men, and men come to feele &amp; to know this: And therefore becauſe it is a true doctrine, they ſay alſo that they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues are ſure, that God hath choſen them, but when they take not the way to become ſure, which S. Peter here hath ſet downe, but goe in a contrary path, &amp; are ſpotted with filthie crimes, wee may boldly ſay, they be lyers: for although they bragge with their tongues of that that they ſhould bee, yet there is a byrde in their breſt, which doth ſing in a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry note, and telleth them plainely what they bee. Another kinde of men there bee, which in no caſe can be perſuaded, that any man may bee ſure of his ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and therfore with ſcoffs they aske
<pb facs="tcp:19443:47"/>
of them which profeſſe the word, when God tolde them ſo? If it were a thing whiche were not to bee, or coulde not be knowne, then the Apoſtle hath great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ouerſhot himſelfe, in telling vs howe wee ſhal come to bee ſure. But aske a queſtion of them, whether they do not beleeue in God, euery one wil anſwere, I put al my whole truſt in him: reaſon then a little further and tel the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that the Scripture which cannot lye, ſaith, That al which truſt in God ſhalbe ſaued: how then wil they ioyne theſe together, that they truſte in GOD, and yet doubt whether they ſhal bee ſaued; Can God deceiue; or ſay they, they know not what; Vndoubtedly if they did know that they haue truſt, they ſhoulde alſo knowe they cannot periſh. But let vs learne by this the miſerie of our time: in which men doe ſtil thinke this doctrine to be ſtraunge. Nowe let vs come to the particuler application of this doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, in which euery one muſt come home to himſelfe, remembring firſt, that ſuche as God hath called home to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,
<pb facs="tcp:19443:48"/>
and choſen to be his children, hee doth alſo giue vnto them true faith and feeling that they bee his elect: and ſuch as perceiue no ſuche thinge in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: are in a very miſerable caſe, and as yet we may ſay forlorne creatures: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore euerye man in him ſelfe muſt aske this queſtion, of his owne ſoule, howe goeth the matter with thee? Art thou ſure GOD hath choſen thee; Doeſt thou feele any aſſurance of eternal life? The conſcience wil anſwere vprightlie if wee be not negligent to make inquirie: then if wee finde this within. I am not ſure, for I doubt and ſtagger: wee muſt inquire without ſelues thus, what is the cauſe, God is faithfull which hath promiſed eternal life vnto all which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue: our heart wil make anſwere, thou regardeſt not the feare of God, thou art ful of foule ſinnes, euill luſtes doe reigne in thee, thou doeſt not ſtudie for the knowledge of Gods word, thou art vnfruiful and barren in good woorkes, therfore thon canſt not ſay, I am led by the ſpirite of God, and therefore ſure I
<pb facs="tcp:19443:48"/>
ſhalbe ſaued: if hee bee wiſe hee will not ſtay heere, as the maner of fooles is, ſaying I am not ſure indeede, neither do I thinke any man can bee, I commit it to God, let him doe with mee what he will: theſe ſpeeches may ſeeme to haue ſome wit and godlineſſe in them, but they are in deede diueliſh and mad, becauſe God hath taught vs a contrary leſſon in this place: but goe this ſteppe further, may I come to this aſſurance? &amp; which is the way? The Lorde doth an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere by his Apoſtle, thou maieſt come to this aſſurance, and pointeth him out the way: euen that which you haue hard, wherein hee muſt painefully trauel and goe forwarde, not for a gird or a braide, and waxe idle againe, but ſtill labour, for theſe men had gone a great way and yet they are willed to proceede ſtill, if the Lorde giue not this aſſurance, wee are to labour ſo much the more, and to bee ſo much the more importunate, to ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect our iudgement, and to ſeeke for knowledge, to call our ſelues to a more ſtraite account, to ſet a watch ouer our affections too ſee with what mynde
<pb facs="tcp:19443:49"/>
wee doe things, to foſter no ſin willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in vs, nor to bee ſlacke to any good worke which God hath appointed, to cal and cry vnto God for faith, and his ſpirite to guide vs, to vſe the meanes di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently which God hath appointed, as the hearing, ſearching, &amp; meditating in the word: thus in time (for it is wrought in men by degrees, &amp; they neuer come to the ful) God will let them ſee that he is their God. That neither life nor death, height or depth, thinges preſent or things to come, Angels, Principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, nor powers, nor any creature ſhall ſeparate vs from his loue in Chriſte. It followeth in the next verſe, For by this meanes an entring ſhalbe miniſtred vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you abundantly into the euerlaſting kingdome of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſte. This is a confirmation of the laſt clauſe of the former ſentence, where he ſaith, If you doe theſe thinges, you ſhal neuer fall: and why? becauſe you ſhal haue a great entrance into the eternal kingdome of Chriſt: as that is a confirmation of the other, where he ſaith, Make your calling and election ſure, as the reaſon foloweth
<pb facs="tcp:19443:49"/>
there, Ye ſhall come to bee ſure: howe? becauſe he which proceedeth ſo far that he knoweth he ſhal neuer fal away from God to deſtruction, hee is, (as it muſt needes bee,) ſure alſo that hee is choſen: for hee ſpeaketh not here of euery parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer fal into ſinne, which is the moſte godly: but ſaith Saint Peter, I tell you if you doe theſe things, yee ſhal neuer fall, not becauſe there is any ſuch ſtablenes in our ſelues, or in our own workes, but wee know they bee the fruites of Gods ſpirite in vs, which is his ſeale, ſet vppon none but thoſe whom he doth mark vp to life eternal, &amp; he is vnchangeable: ſo it foloweth here, ye ſhal not fal, for they that haue a rich entrance into the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſte, which is euerlaſting, ſo that Chriſte doth reigne in them, as hee doth in all the faithful by his ſpirite, can not fal, vntil the power of Chriſte faile, and his kingdome come to an end. For we muſt note, that the force of the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, reſteth in the difference which is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the kingdome of Chriſt and the kingdomes of this worlde: in which though they bee neuer ſo mightie, &amp; ful
<pb facs="tcp:19443:50"/>
of policie and wiſedome, yet they ſhould come to and ende: and therefore a man cannot rightly ſay vnto the ſubiects, you haue a mightie Prince, who is bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and gracious, your peace therefore and happie eſtate ſhall endure for euer: naye, the mightie may bee ouercome, if not by men, at leaſtwiſe by death, and ſo they may be to day in peace and good eſtate, to morowe al in an vprore, to day vnder a louing and gracious Prince, to morowe vnder a fierce tyrant: ſo vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine is the ſtate of the kingdom of this worlde: but in the kingdome of Chriſte, whoſe power is aboue al, and can neuer come to an ende, but is as he ſaith here, eternal, it is farre otherwiſe, becauſe his ſtate is vnchangeable, ſo is theirs that be once entred thereinto, and therefore are ſure they can neuer fal. Whoſoeuer doth but eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtreightly looke ouer theſe words of the apoſtle, if he haue any ſight at al, he muſt needes confeſſe al this, the matter is ſo cleere, that we can but mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel how it ſhould come to paſſe that this doctrine of the Lord, ſet foorth by his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, ſhould finde ſo few friendes, and
<pb facs="tcp:19443:50"/>
ſo many extreeme enemies: but indeed men which are lyers, doe in this thing confes the truth, that they feele not any ſuch matter, &amp; therfore cannot abide to heare that al true godly men, &amp; faithfull Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s haue this knowledge in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: but let vs giue eare to the Apoſtle, who telleth vs how we ſhal com to haue Chriſte to be our king, &amp; to reigne ouer vs, namely if we yeld vp our ſelues to the gouernance of his ſpirit, which worketh al goodnes in our hearts, ſubduing and va<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quiſhing al the rebels which we beare about in vs. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trariwiſe it muſt needs be graunted, the ſuch as are beaſtly Epicures, folowing their own fleſhly mind, letting loſe the raines, &amp; giuing the ſwing vnto the raging luſtes of the fleſhe, deſpiſing the knowledge of Gods wil, &amp; therefore regard not his worde: though with full mouth they cal Chriſt their king &amp; their lord: yet when god ſaith here by his apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, that the entrance into his kingdom is by this means, that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> folow after ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tue, knowledge and godlines: they ſhew that they be none of his ſubiects, being altogether void of his ſpirit, but the bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d
<pb facs="tcp:19443:51"/>
ſlaues of ſin and Satan, whoſe kingdome they vphold, with tooth &amp; naile: &amp; that maketh them, euen as thoſe which are of another Corporatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to fight againſt the truth, &amp; thoſe which profeſſe it: deuiſing al the colours &amp; ſhifts they can to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſin, inuenting al the ſlanders that may be to diſcredite the godly conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of ſuch as folow the way here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed: condemning them as ouer pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe &amp; curious, if they do but looke this way which God willeth al his ſeruantes to walk: if God doe open their eyes, to ſee but eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in a glimmering, that whiche he doth teach in this place, they woulde be aſhamed of their maſter and bluſh at that, which now they boaſte &amp; brag of: they would alſo confeſſe that like blinde buzzards and madde beaſts, they haue fought againſt God, &amp; not men: finally it would make them change their waies, and ſeeke diligently to haue the witnes within themſelues, that they bee the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of God. We muſt marke wel one other thing which is here ſpoken, to wit that he ſaith an entra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſhalbe miniſtred vnto you, abundantly or richly: as if hee
<pb facs="tcp:19443:51"/>
ſhould ſay, when ye haue labored &amp; tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelled, to bee as it were wel ſoked &amp; ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned in godlines, &amp; plentifully decked with al graces &amp; gifts of the ſpirit, ye ſhal by degrees proceede ſo far, and gaine ſo much, that your entrance into the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt ſhalbe very great: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon it doth folow, that they ſhalbe paſt danger, &amp; may wel warrant themſelues, of ſure ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding in aſmuch as Chriſt hath not onely begun to reigne in them, and to bee their king, but alſo in great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and mightily. But doth he not adde this one worde more then needeth; Is it not enough to haue an entrance, vnleſſe wee haue a riche entrance into his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; doth Chriſt once begin to reigne in a man, and to driue out the power of Satan, and afterward caſt him of againe to deſtruction; I anſwere that this word is not added in vaine, for wee be taught thereby to take heede that wee content not our ſelues with ſome litle taſte and ſmal entrance: for his purpoſe is to make a difference betweene ſuche on the one part as make ſome beginning, and haue ſome good deſires &amp; motions in them,
<pb facs="tcp:19443:52"/>
and do taſte of the good word of God, and are in ſome ſort lightned, but ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come with ſinful luſtes, &amp; vaine delights of the fleſh, they ſlide back againe ſoden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they were but for a brunt, it bringeth foorth no ripe fruite in them, neither to ſpeake properly, did Chriſte euer reigne in them: and ſuch on the other part as proceede vnto the deepe rooting out of ſinne, &amp; ſure and faſt planting the truth in their heartes, going forwarde dayly from grace to grace, and from ſtrength to ſtrength, vntil Chriſte haue ſet vp his throne in them, and beare ſway, to the ouerthrow of the power of darknes, and bereuing the Diuel of the intereſt hee had, and thruſting him from the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion which hee helde: a doctrine which muſt needes doe vs much good if wee bleeue it: and very needefull to be vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged inſtantly, conſidering the nature &amp; diſpoſition of men at this day: they are afraide of going too farre in vertue and knowledge, they count it a needleſſe thing to bee admoniſhed or taught di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligentlie, they take great ſcorne to bee counted ſuch as may bee amended, yea
<pb facs="tcp:19443:52"/>
and that which is more, when as they haue not learned the firſt pointe of a Chriſtian ſcholler, they will ſeeme per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect: ſo farre are they from hauing this abundant entring into the kingome of Chriſte.</p>
            <p>Learne heere therefore, dearely belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and learne it wel, lay ſure hold ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of that it do not ſlip from you, for God teacheth vs heere the onely way to life and happines: let go the vaine dreames &amp; doltiſh opinions of people ſotted in their ignorance, which are ſo far blinded by the malice of Satan, that which way ſoeuer they goe, ſtill they are in hope of eternal glory, as though the way to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen were ſo brode that a man could not goe out of it, and the entrance ſo eaſie, that he may enter when he wil: for this is the diuinitie of our time: howſoeuer a man ſpend his time in ignorance, not caring for, nor ſeeking after the true knowledge of god, howſoeuer he be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed with foule &amp; beaſtly ſinnes, that in deed there be nothing in him but pride, ſelf loue, vaine glory, enuie, gluttony, the luſtes of adulterie, and ſuch like, yea, ſo
<pb facs="tcp:19443:53"/>
farre, that the ſcripture doeth liken him to a ſwine or a dogge: yet if as they ſay, hee haue God in his minde, and can ſay, Lorde haue mercy vpon mee, they thinke this is all that can bee requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of men, they wil not ſticke to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite al ſuche: beeing nothing at al ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with that, which God telleth in this place by his Apoſtle, howe farre men muſt proceede in his feare before they can wel warrant themſelues to bee in good caſe. For ye may as wel ioyne heauen and hell together, fire and water wil aſſoone agree, light and darkeneſſe, are as like one another, as the common faith is to that whiche wee are taught in this place. But I wil returne to applie this doctrine to the godly, for whom it is written: howe they may, as wee vſe to ſay, make this thing dead ſure: for there is many a godly man, which after long trauel, and muche care to pleaſe God, is yet ſo matched with ſtubborn nature ſo deepely infected and poyſoned with ſinne, that he is compelled, although he haue gained muche and doeth feele the power of Gods ſpirit in him, ſometimes
<pb facs="tcp:19443:53"/>
to bee in doubt, and to thinke his labor but loſt, becauſe hee cannot get ſo great a victorie as he would faine: let not this man be diſmaied, but let him goe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, remembring what is here promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: the more hee wanteth, the more let him ſtriue, and hee ſhal plainly perceiue, that God regardeth his care and trauel, conſidereth his ſighes and grones, and wil perfourme all his deſires: let him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that theſe men whome S. Peter wrote vnto, had obteined the precious faith, did knowe and were eſtabliſhed in the preſent truth, &amp; yet they were not ſo far but that they may bee moued to make their election ſure, to ſeeke a further en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into the kingdom of Chriſt: &amp; ſo to continue that which was but begun. We ought the more to be moued here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, becauſe the worlde is euer full of fearful examples, which if they were wel conſidered, wold make a mans haire to ſtand vpright, when hee ſhal ſee that for want of this doctrine, or at the leaſt the not practiſing of it, ther be many which ſeeme not only to haue had ſome good liking of the truth, but alſo a great zeale,
<pb facs="tcp:19443:54"/>
euen to ſuffer ſome what for the ſame, which are become euen as cold as yſe, &amp; ſcarce any point of god lines left in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: yea though they would beare me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that they haue, like good ſchollers pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded to the higheſt fourme, yet when our great maſter ſhal poſe them, they ſhal not be alowed to ſit in the loweſt: ſo dangerous a thing it is once to relent or ſlacken our care, vntil wee haue gotten this ful aſſurance, and made this rich en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into the kingdom of Chriſt, that wee feele our ſelues to be led by the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, and feele it, not by any vaine conceit of our owne fooliſh braine, nor by ſenſles ſecuritie, but by the working and fruits of the ſame ſpirit. If this were wel weighed, men woulde not content themſelues with ſo litle, or nothing: they woulde not make ſo light account of teaching: they would leaue of their ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous and reprochful raylinges: they would not like filthie ſwine wallow the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſtil in the filthie mire of their ſins: they would not prattle ſo much of this, that al are ſinners, and therefore thinke al are alike, ſhuffeling together one with
<pb facs="tcp:19443:54"/>
another: nay God wil ſunder them, for he hath taught here who bee godly and faithful, ſuch as he taketh and accepteth for his children: and who bee vn godly Infidels, children of the diuel, and heires of hel. For in very deede, though al bee ſinners, yet they greatly differ, for ſome continue in their ſinnes, ſeducing &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing themſelues with vaine hope of Gods mercy: ſome do repent after the maner here preſcribed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in this, that they clenſe themſelues more and more from al filthines of the fleſhe, and growe in al vertues and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, vntil they be decked in their ſoules, with heauenly ornaments, and haue yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vp them ſelues too haue Chriſte raigne in them. As for the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, to crie only with words for mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, in ſome light meaſure to be greeued, to feare the iudgementes of God, and yet the ſoule within nothing changed, nor the ſpirite renued, nor Chriſte raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in the heart: it doth but deceiue all which truſt to it. Moſt true it is, that what time ſoeuer a ſinner doth repent, hee is forgiuen: but this is as like to that repen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tance,
<pb facs="tcp:19443:55"/>
which is here by S, Peter deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, as we ſay, an Apple is to an Oyſter: forif wee looke wel vnto them both, we ſhal finde them to agree in very fewe thinges, and thoſe euen the leaſt. Let vs I ſay once again faſten our ſteppes in this way, let vs goe forward, and not ſo much as loke back, vntil ſuch time as we haue by our owne experience, proued that to bee true which is taught by Saint Peter. For it is not enough to beleeue that this is true (although that be ſomwhat) vnles wee trie it to bee ſo by our ſelues. Hee is now a ſtark foole which ſeeth this to be the only way to happines, and for ſlouth wil not walke in it: as though the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of heauen were not worth the tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelling for. We may gather alſo in this place, if wee bee not ſenſles<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> howe great enemies they be to the ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of men: which would vtterly debar them of the worde, that is appointed to bee the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument by which god worketh al theſe good things in his ſeruants: for with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the (as it may be eaſily gathered here) we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do nothing. It doth alſo appeare, that thoſe are in a miſerable caſe, whoſe
<pb facs="tcp:19443:55"/>
office and duetie is, not onlie to ſhewe men ſome part of Gods will, but to bring them thus far as S. Peter doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, if they be not wel furniſhed, and haue walked firſt this way themſelues: for how ſhal they bring other men, to that, which themſelues haue not, nor knowe not; It doeth appeare alſo that God hath ſhewed a ſore iudgement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that people, whiche haue ſuche a guide as cannot ſhewe them this way: which is the onely way to heauen: for doubtleſſe it is more then if he ſhoulde thunder vpon them from heauen, or fire their houſes ouer their heads: eſpecially when they are ſo blind, that they ſee not the plague, but thinke themſelues in bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter caſe then thoſe whome God doth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer rule by his word. But woe, &amp; woe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine be to thoſe blinde guides, &amp; ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards, which doe not feed: &amp; wretched is that people which are as ſheepe with, out a ſhepheard. For how ſhall they euer heare of theſe things; We can but pitie their miſery, and deſire the Lord to ſend redreſſe, in ſo lamentable and deſperate a caſe: which is thought to be nothing.
<pb facs="tcp:19443:56"/>
becauſe indeed the moſt men know no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: for had they but knowne what god requireth in that man whom he wil ſaue, though they were not partakers of it themſelues, yet they would conſent &amp; agree to the doctrine: and confeſſe that there is no way to attain eternal life, but by ſo ſound teaching as may bring peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to the things here required. But I wil here make an end.</p>
            <p>O Lorde graunt, that this doctrine which thou haſt taught vs in this thy ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly word, may enter into vs, &amp; dwel in vs for euer: that ſo we may be ſure of thy fauour and of eternal life, through Ieſus Chriſte thy deare ſonne our Lorde and only ſauiour.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:19443:56"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
